<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<schedule>
  <conference>
    <title>27th Chaos Communication Congress</title>
    <subtitle>We come in peace</subtitle>
    <venue>bcc</venue>
    <city>Berlin</city>
    <start>2010-12-27</start>
    <end>2010-12-30</end>
    <days>4</days>
    <release>Version 0.35b</release>
    <day_change>04:00</day_change>
    <timeslot_duration>00:15</timeslot_duration>
  </conference>
  <day date="2010-12-27" index="1">
    <room name="Saal 1">
      <event id="4253">
        <start>00:15</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 1</room>
        <slug>pentanews_game_show</slug>
        <title>Pentanews Game Show</title>
        <subtitle>Your opponents will be riddled as well</subtitle>
        <track>Community</track>
        <type>other</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>Out of the news section of the [C3D2](http://www.c3d2.de "CCC Dresden") [radio programme](http://www.pentamedia.org/pentaradio Pentaradio24) we've compiled an entertaining game show, an Internet-based multiplayer "Who becomes millionaire?" challenge. The audience and folks on the peace missions are asked to help the players.</abstract>
        <description>From the collected news items of our monthly radio show we've generated a game show somewhat inspired by "Who becomes millionaire?" but multi player. The questions cover all types of net-news we've found interesting to mention in our radio show.

An example question would be: "Who operates the biggest Cloud service?"
# Google
# Facebook
# Amazon
# Botnets

This game show was successfully beta tested at the [Datenspuren](http://www.datenspuren.de "Datenspuren") symposium this year but much improved since.
                             
Honouring English as the language spoken by the most people at the congress we offer English and German depending on the audience.
</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="5">Alien8</person>
          <person id="26">Astro</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
          <link href="http://pentamedia.org     ">Radio</link>
          <link href="http://www.datenspuren.de">http://www.datenspuren.de</link>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4302">
        <start>11:30</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 1</room>
        <slug>27c3_keynote_we_come_in_peace</slug>
        <title>27C3 Keynote</title>
        <subtitle>We come in Peace</subtitle>
        <track>Society</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract></abstract>
        <description></description>
        <persons>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4103">
        <start>12:45</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 1</room>
        <slug>copyright_enforcement_versus_freedoms</slug>
        <title>Copyright Enforcement Vs. Freedoms</title>
        <subtitle>ACTA, IPRED3 and other upcoming battles of the crusade against sharing</subtitle>
        <track>Society</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>ACTA, upcoming criminal enforcement directive, filtering of content... The entertainment industries go further and further into their crusade against sharing. They not only attack our fundamental freedoms, but also the very essence of the Internet.

This session is a panorama of the current and upcoming battles, campaigns and actions. Everyone can help defeat the motherf#&#167;$ers!</abstract>
        <description>The crusade against sharing the entertainment industries are waging against their customers is taking new directions. 

Their obsession to apply models from the past to today's technologies leads these industries to turn copyright against their customers. Direct consequences would be damages to freedom of expression, privacy and the right to a fair trial, that would greatly serve the will of some politicians to control the Internet.

A number of extremely disturbing trends and upcoming legislative projects will be detailed in this session:

- ACTA. The "Anti-Counterfeiting Trade Agreement" is the flagship of the entertainment industries. It is a prototype of how to impose legislation while circumventing democratic process and public opinions. ACTA contains most of what the industries are dreaming about. By putting legal and monetary pressure over Internet technical intermediates, ACTA would force them to act as private copyright police and justice of the Net.

- IPRED2. The criminal enforcement directive was frozen in the Council of EU in 2006. It is about to be revived under the direction of the French commissioner Michel Barnier. It may contain sanctions for "inciting, aiding and abetting" infringement, which would blur the line between copyright infringement and political speech or the production of software and on-line services.

- "voluntary agreements", "extra-judicial measures", and "cooperation between rights-holders and Internet service providers" sound harmless, but they represent a growing trend in trying to force the ISPs into policing, through contracts, their networks and users. ISPs would be forced to use access restrictions ("three strikes") or even content filtering. 

- Revision of the e-Commerce directive. The movie and music industries will use this occasion to attack the exoneration of liability for technical intermediates of the Net, with potential consequences on freedom of speech.

- Filtering of the Net. In the name of protecting the children or gamblers, it is being deployed all over Europe. These first steps will allow to further expand filtering mechanisms for the purpose of copyright enforcement, under influence the entertainment industries. 

How those policies are put in place? What can a citizen do in order to help counter them? How can we better organize to gain momentum in protecting fundamental freedoms in the digital environment? What were the successful campaigns so far, and what will be the upcoming ones?

Join us in our effort!</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="1505">J&#233;r&#233;mie Zimmermann</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
          <link href="http://laquadrature.net">La Quadrature du Net</link>
          <link href="http://www.laquadrature.net/en/robocopyright-acta-video">[video] Robocopyright ACTA</link>
          <link href="http://laquadrature.net/ACTA">La Quadrature's web-dossier on ACTA</link>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4252">
        <start>14:00</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 1</room>
        <slug>von_zensursula_ueber_censilia_zum_kindernet</slug>
        <title>Von Zensursula &#252;ber Censilia hin zum Kindernet</title>
        <subtitle>Jahresr&#252;ckblick rund um Internet-Sperren, Sendezeitbegrenzungen im Internet und vermeintlichen Jugendschutz</subtitle>
        <track>Society</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>de</language>
        <abstract>Nach Zensursula kam Censilia und das Kindernet: 2010 brachte nach den hitzigen Diskussionen um Internet-Sperren und das Zugangserschwerungsgesetz einige neue Entwicklungen &#8211; und die Rundfunkkommission der L&#228;nder will mal wieder den Jugendschutz im Internet angehen.</abstract>
        <description>Der Vortrag l&#228;sst die Themen noch einmal Revue passieren und bringt einen Ausblick, was uns in den n&#228;chsten Monaten eventuell noch bl&#252;ht.</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="2714">Alvar C. H. Freude</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4185">
        <start>16:00</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 1</room>
        <slug>whistleblowing__licht_ins_dunkel</slug>
        <title>Whistleblowing</title>
        <subtitle>Licht ins Dunkel!</subtitle>
        <track>Society</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>de</language>
        <abstract>Whistleblowing als universelles Konzept f&#252;r mehr Transparenz &#8211; oder: &#252;ber die R&#252;ckeroberung der Dunkelr&#228;ume in Wirtschaft und Politik auch jenseits von Wikileaks.</abstract>
        <description>Die Pr&#228;sentation von Wikileaks war einer der H&#246;hepunkte der 26C3. Durch Wikileaks haben viele Hacker erstmals von Whistleblowing erfahren. Allerdings verk&#252;rzen einige Whistleblowing auch auf die anonyme Ver&#246;ffentlichung brisanter Dokumente im Netz. Dem wollen Guido Strack und Johannes Ludwig vom Whistleblower-Netzwerk Deutschland mit ihrem Vortrag und einer begleitenden Ausstellung entgegenwirken.
 
Es werden Beispiele von Menschen gezeigt, die Zivilcourage an ihrem Arbeitsplatz bewiesen und teils offen, teils anonym, auf Missst&#228;nde aufmerksam gemacht haben. Es wird dargestellt, dass diese Menschen von Kollegen und Rechtsordnung oft alleine gelassen werden und auch wo die Grenzen anonymer Hinweise und die Schwierigkeiten journalistischen Umgangs mit Whistleblowern liegen.
Die Referenten erl&#228;utern wie Whistleblowing ein archimedischer Punkt werden k&#246;nnte, um Licht in Dunkelr&#228;ume in Wirtschaft und Politik zu bringen, die Methoden der Hinterm&#228;nner der Macht offen zu legen und Risiken f&#252;r &#246;ffentliche Interessen rechtzeitig erkennen zu k&#246;nnen.
 
Ansatzpunkte hierzu sind das Hinterfragen der Legitimit&#228;t und Reichweite von (so genannten Sicherheitsrelevanten- oder Betriebs- und Gesch&#228;fts-) Geheimnissen, eine Vernetzung der Zivilgesellschaft und kritischer Medien zur Organisation von Gegenmacht, effektiver rechtlicher Schutz von Whistleblowern und ein anderer kultureller Umgang mit jenen, die bisher oft als Denunzianten oder Nestbeschmutzer verunglimpft werden.
 
Durch Einblicke in die Arbeit von Whistleblower-Netzwerk e.V. und seiner internationalen Kooperationspartner wird schlie&#223;lich aufgezeigt wie einige dieser Ansatzpunkte bereits konkret angegangen werden, aber auch wo noch Unterst&#252;tzung n&#246;tig ist und was die Netzgemeinde hier leisten k&#246;nnte.</description>
        <persons>
        </persons>
        <links>
          <link href="http://whistleblower-net.de">Hompage des Whistleblower-Netzwerk e.V.</link>
          <link href="http://ansTageslicht.de">Hompage des DokZentrums ansTageslicht.de</link>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4190">
        <start>20:30</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 1</room>
        <slug>data_retention_in_the_eu</slug>
        <title>Data Retention in the EU five years after the Directive</title>
        <subtitle>Why the time is now to get active</subtitle>
        <track>Society</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language></language>
        <abstract>2011 will again be a crucial year in the battle against data retention and blanket surveillance. The EU Commission is planning to publish its review of the directive in December (right in time before 27C3), and the lobbying and PR battle has already begun. In six months from now, we will see the legislative proposal from the EU commission for the revision of data retention.

The talk will give a full picture of the legal state of play, what is going on in Brussels, what is already being done and of course where you can help. The speakers are closely involved in the process on the European and national level.</abstract>
        <description>In December 2005, the European Parliament agreed to the data retention directive that introduced mandatory retention of the telecommunications behaviour of half a billion EU citizens and residents. That was a huge disappointment and perceived by many as the final opening of the floodgates. Frank Rieger and Rop Gongrijp at 22C3 even declared that "we lost the war" over privacy. But things turned out different than expected.

Now, five years later, a new privacy movement has risen in Germany and elsewhere, a number of constitutional courts all across Europe have declared national data retention laws illegal, a case against the whole directive is pending at the European Court of Justice, and the EU has a justice commissioner who openly said that she would not have suggested the whole thing in the first place, and a home affairs commissioner who voted against the directive when she was still a Member of Parliament.

The talk will give a full picture of the legal state of play, what is going on in Brussels, what is already being done and of course where you can help. The speakers are all active in European Digital Rights (EDRi.org) and are closely involved in the process on the European and national level.</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="3197">axel</person>
          <person id="3172">Katarzyna Szymielewicz</person>
          <person id="1207">Patrick  Breyer</person>
          <person id="336">Ralf Bendrath</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
          <link href="http://EDRi.org">EDRi.org</link>
        </links>
      </event>
    </room>
    <room name="Saal 2">
      <event id="4096">
        <start>12:45</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 2</room>
        <slug>code_deobfuscation_by_optimization</slug>
        <title>Code deobfuscation by optimization</title>
        <subtitle></subtitle>
        <track>Hacking</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>Optimization algorithms present an effective way for removing most obfuscations that are used today. Much of the compiler theory can be applied in removing obfuscations and building fast and reliable deobfuscation systems. By understanding traditional optimization problems and techniques it is possible to develop and customize compiler optimization algorithms for usage in binary deobfuscation/analysis.</abstract>
        <description>Analysis of malware binaries is constantly becoming more difficult with introduction of many different types of code obfuscators. One common theme in all obfuscators is transformation of code into a complex representation. This process can be viewed as inverse of compiler optimization techniques and as such can be partially removed using optimization algorithms.   
Optimization algorithms present an effective way for removing most obfuscations that are used today. Much of the compiler theory can be applied in removing obfuscations and building fast and reliable deobfuscation systems. By understanding traditional optimization problems and techniques it is possible to develop and customize compiler optimization algorithms for usage in binary deobfuscation/analysis.  
Optimization algorithms are especially successful in following:  
&#8226; Removal of no operation instructions  
&#8226; Simplifying complex instructions  
&#8226; Removal of unconditional jumps  
&#8226; Removal of conditional jumps  
&#8226; Simplifying control-flow graph  
  
This presentation shows common obfuscation techniques and a process of adapting optimization algorithms for removing obfuscations. 
Additionally, a open-source plug-in for the IDA Pro disassembler is presented that demonstrates usability of the proposed optimization process as well as a set of techniques to speed up the process of analyzing obfuscated code.   
</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="2986">Branko Spasojevic</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
          <link href="http://os2.zemris.fer.hr/ns/malware/2010_spasojevic/Diplomski_Spasojevic.pdf">Paper that describes in more detail presentation material. </link>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4140">
        <start>14:00</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 2</room>
        <slug>contemporary_profiling_of_web_users</slug>
        <title>Contemporary Profiling of Web Users</title>
        <subtitle>On Using Anonymizers and Still Get Fucked</subtitle>
        <track>Hacking</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>This talk will provide a summary of recently discovered methods which allow to break the Internet's privacy and anonymity.
</abstract>
        <description> We will show, amongst others: 

* ways of distinguishing bots from humans. We use this technique to provide crawlers with false data or lure them into tar pits.
 
Other than CAPTCHAs we introduce methods that profile the holistic behaviour within a single web session to distinguish users or bots within a longer timeframe based on subtle charactistics in most bots'  implementations.

* breaking filtering of JavaScript in web-based proxies.

While next to all web proxies advertise the capability of filtering JavaScript, the ubiqity of XSS and CSRF attacks have proven that correct filtering of arbitrary HTML is extremly difficult.

* track and re-identifying users based upon their web-profile.

We show how a third-party observer (e. g. proxy server or DNS server) can create a long-term profile of roaming web users using only statistical patterns mined from their web traffic. These patterns are used to track users by linking multiple surfing sessions. Our attack does not rely on cookies or other unique identifiers, but exploits chatacteristic patterns of frequently accessed hosts. We demonstrate that such statistical attacks are practicable and we will also look into basic defense strategies.

* traffic analysis and fingerprinting attacks on users of anonymizing networks.

Even if anonymizeres like Tor are used, a local adversary can measure the volume of transfered data and timing characteristics to e. g. determine the retrieved websites. We will shortly sketch the current state of the art in traffic analysis, which has been improved significantly within the last year.</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="3175">Dominik Herrmann</person>
          <person id="2181">lexi</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4111">
        <start>16:00</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 2</room>
        <slug>eins_zwei_drei_alle_sind_dabei</slug>
        <title>Eins, zwei, drei - alle sind dabei</title>
        <subtitle>Von der Volksz&#228;hlung zum Bundesmelderegister</subtitle>
        <track>Society</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>de</language>
        <abstract>Neben einer kurzen Einf&#252;hrung in die Problematik des Zensus 2011, soll es in dem Vortrag auch &#252;ber die CCC Stellungnahmen f&#252;r mehrere Landetage gehen. Weiterhin geht es auch um die mittlerweile abgewiesene Verfassungsbeschwerde des AK Zensus sowie weitere M&#246;glichkeiten "was zu machen".</abstract>
        <description>Zur Verhinderung einer zivilgesellschaftlichen Bewegung gegen eine neuerliche Volksz&#228;hlung, erarbeitete die amtliche Statistik seit mehr als 10 Jahren das jetzt geplante alternative Erfassungsverfahren, genannt &#8222;registergest&#252;tzter Zensus&#8220;, bei dem nur noch rund 25% der Bev&#246;lkerung mit pers&#246;nlichen Frageb&#246;gen beschickt werden m&#252;ssen. In der ersten Stufe der Volksz&#228;hlung werden Daten von verschiedensten Stellen erfasst und bei den Landesstatistik&#228;mtern und dem Bundesstatistikamt in einer noch nie dagewesenen Datenbank zusammengef&#252;hrt. Erst wenn dieser bisher unvorstellbare Datenberg angeh&#228;uft wurde, kommen die Bundesl&#228;nder bzw. deren Ausf&#252;hrungsgesetze ins Spiel. Das f&#252;hrt dazu, dass die zu erwartende gesellschaftliche Diskussion erst stattfinden wird, wenn das Kind schon im Brunnen ertrunken ist.

Der Vortrag versucht den interessierten Zuh&#246;rern einen m&#246;glichst umfassenden, aber bestimmt nicht langweiligen &#220;berblick &#252;ber die Thematik Zensus 2011 zu geben.

Selbstverst&#228;ndlich muss im Rahmen solch eines Vortrags auch dar&#252;ber gesprochen werden, warum die Verfassungsbeschwerde gegen das ZensG 2011 mit immerhin 13000 Unterst&#252;tzern abgewiesen wurde und wie es jetzt weitergeht.
</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="2349">Oliver "Unicorn" Knapp</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4164">
        <start>17:15</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 2</room>
        <slug>friede_sei_mit_euren_daten</slug>
        <title>Friede sei mit Euren Daten</title>
        <subtitle>Ein datenschutzrechtlicher Ausflug in ein kirchliches Parelleluniversum</subtitle>
        <track>Society</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language></language>
        <abstract>Bundesdeutscher und kirchlicher Datenschutz f&#252;hren eine Parallelexistenz. W&#228;hrend das Bundesdatenschutzgesetz von der &#214;ffentlichkeit wahrgenommen und kritisch begleitet wird, ist den Wenigsten &#252;berhaupt klar, dass es auch einen vom BDSG losgel&#246;sten Datenschutz innerhalb der Kirchen gibt, der sich in einigen wichtigen Punkten vom staatlichen unterscheidet. Dieser Vortrag soll das Bewusstsein f&#252;r ein Recht wecken, von dem sechzig Prozent der Deutschen betroffen sind &#8211; oft ohne es zu wissen. Praxisbeispiele und Tipps inbegriffen.</abstract>
        <description>F&#252;r knapp f&#252;nfzig Millionen Menschen in Deutschland gilt das Bundesdatenschutzgesetz nur eingeschr&#228;nkt. Grund: Sie sind Mitglied einer der beiden Amtskirchen. Diese haben sich noch aus Weimarer Zeit das Privileg eines teilweise vom staatlichen Recht abgekoppelten Rechtswesens bewahrt. Man merkt dies besonders frappierend bei der bisweilen sehr eigenwilligen Verfolgung von Kindervergewaltigung, aber auch viel weniger sensationell im t&#228;glichen Leben beim Umgang mit personenbezogenen Daten, wie sie im Religionsunterricht, bei Amtshandlungen oder ganz schlicht bei Raumvermietungen anfallen. Die Kirchen stehen im Spagat, eigentlich mit Datenschutz wenig am Hut zu haben, gleichzeitig aber in der Seelsorge absolute Verschiegenheit bewahren zu wollen. Beginnend mit einem theoretischen Einstieg beschreibt dieser Vortrag anhand mehrerer Praxisbeispiele Gemeinsamkeiten und Unterschiede zwischen kirchlichem und staatlichem Datenschutz, zeigt, wo man selbst als Nicht-Kirchenmitglied vom innerkirchlichen Recht betroffen ist, benennt L&#252;cken, an denen Handlungsbedarf besteht, und gibt Tipps, wie man innerhalb dieser Organisationen f&#252;r besseren Datenschutz sorgen kann und wie man auch als Au&#223;enstehender daf&#252;r sorgt, dass mit den eigenen Daten kein Unfug getrieben wird. Hierbei werden sowohl rechtliche als auch technische Aspekte angesprochen.</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="2873">Jochim Selzer</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
          <link href="http://www.ekd.de/datenschutz/4650.html">Datenschutzgesetz der EKD</link>
          <link href="http://www.ekd.de/datenschutz/4656.html">Datenschutzdurchf&#252;hrungsverordnung der Evangelischen Kirche im Rheinland</link>
          <link href="http://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;source=web&amp;cd=3&amp;ved=0CB8QFjAC&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.ekir.de%2Fbonn%2Fdownloads%2FOrganigramm_-4c-KKBonn0906.pdf&amp;rct=j&amp;q=%22jochim%20selzer%22%20datenschutzbeauftragter&amp;ei=dnuvTJrWAsTOswbamenJDQ&amp;usg=AFQjCNF70KpJ3-rrotPTXHP5qRa8uMLt7w&amp;sig2=CzhXeX7hq-X9fp_FV3db4g&amp;cad=rja">Organigramm des Kirchenkreises Bonn</link>
          <link href="http://www.gesetze-im-internet.de/bdsg_1990/">Bundesdatenschutzgesetz</link>
          <link href="http://www.gesetze-im-internet.de/gg/index.html">Grundgesetz</link>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4265">
        <start>18:30</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 2</room>
        <slug>hacking_smart_phones</slug>
        <title>hacking smart phones</title>
        <subtitle>expanding the attack surface and then some</subtitle>
        <track>Hacking</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language></language>
        <abstract>There's been a fair bit written and presented about smartphone's, and yet, when it comes to the attack surface of the operating systems running on them, and the applications running on top of those, much still has to be explorer. This talk will dive a bit deeper into that attack surface.</abstract>
        <description>This talk will take a look at the smart phone attack surface, only from and end-to-end point of view. the baseband type stuff and things owned by the telco's will not be covered. Basically, it'll cover 5 major areas: 

- identifying operating systems (through for example the user-agent with mms) 
- identifying entrypoints 
- identifying trust boundaries 
- identifying bugs 
- exploiting bugs 

There has been a fair amount of cellphone and smartphone reseach done in the past, and yet, when it comes to attack surface, we've barely scratched the surface. SMS alone allows for a dozen or so different types of messages, there's mms, all sorts of media codecs are build into smart phones. The entrypoints can be roughly categorized as: 

primary entypoints:
	- zero-click remote attacks over default communication network (sms, mms, ...)
secondary entrypoints:
	- zero-click remote attacks over non-default communication network (email, ...) 
tertiary entrypoints: 
	- proximity attacks (wifi, bluetooth, irda, mitm wifi connection, ...)
	- not-zero click remote attacks  (e.g. start application XYZ and connect to my evil server)

The main focus in this talk will be on the primary entrypoints, however some of the secondary and tertiary entrypoints will be talked about aswell, in particular irda, since unlike bluetooth and wifi, very little security research has ever been done with irda, which on itself is weird, since after less than a day of poking around it became quite clear most irda stacks are pretty weak (as a hilarious irda sidenote which got me started to look at idra, one should read the following microsoft bulletin http://www.microsoft.com/technet/security/bulletin/ms01-046.mspx). 

once's the interesting entrypoints for various smartphones are explored the talk will dive into some of the trust boundaries on different smartphones, things their sandboxes allow, things they don't, wether or not it's documented and wether or not the documentation is actually accurate. 

in the spirit of keeping the best for last, some of the bugs discovered during the smartphone research will be discussed, both the details of them, as well as the pains the speaker had to go through to make exploits for them. </description>
        <persons>
          <person id="3158">Ilja van Sprundel</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4017">
        <start>20:30</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 2</room>
        <slug>desktop_on_the_linux</slug>
        <title>Desktop on the Linux... (and BSD, of course)</title>
        <subtitle>you're doing it confused? weird? strange? wrong?</subtitle>
        <track>Community</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>Time to take a look back and under the hood of the current state of FOSS based desktops: The Good, The Bad and The Ugly &#8211; Bloat, strange APIs, too much complexity.</abstract>
        <description>The first decade of the 21st century brought huge progress in the development of FOSS Desktop systems. Users can now choose from a broad range of environments, which all adhere to a coherent set of standards. Not to forget that FOSS did even pioneer some GUI technologies which were later adopted by other (read: non free) systems.

There's one year left of this decade. Time to take a look back and under the hood of the current state of FOSS based desktops: The Good, The Bad and The Ugly.

- "Yo Dawg!" Stacking layers of redundancy. (Phonon -&gt; GStreamer -&gt; Pulseaudio)

- Do you really need a full blown desktop session for a login screen? (GDM &gt;2.21)

- The graphics subsystem (X11) is network transparent and provides IPC. So let's build our own IPC system, that's not network transparent (DBus).

- I think the login process is not complicated enough yet. (ConsoleKit)

- Good ideas, poor implementation, abusive use. (PolicyKit)

- Making things happen automatically doesn't "make things just work!". (Network Manager, ivman, HAL based mount)

- Unified configuration madness. (gconf, XSettings)

- Zombies: Some things are so bad, that even their original creators now abandon them (HAL).

- What if special use cases require you, to get rid of some or multiple of the above? Admin's Nightmares!

and last but not least

- Possible security flaws in each of the above.

And of course we'll also look at some of the pearls of strange API design in some of the above.</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="2477">datenwolf</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="3957">
        <start>21:45</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 2</room>
        <slug>ipv6_insecurities</slug>
        <title>Recent advances in IPv6 insecurities</title>
        <subtitle></subtitle>
        <track>Hacking</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>New protocol features have been proposed and implemented in the last 5 years and ISPs are now slowly starting to deploy IPv6. This talk starts with a brief summary of the issues presented five years ago, and then expands on the new risks.
Discovered implemention security issues in Windows 7/2008, Linux and Cisco will be shown too. Comes with a GPL'ed toolkit: thc-ipv6</abstract>
        <description>Five years have past since my initial talk on IPv6 insecurities at the CCC Congress.
New protocol features have been proposed and implemented since then and ISPs are now slowly starting to deploy IPv6.
Few changes have led to a better security of the protocol, several increase the risk instead.
This talk starts with a brief summary of the issues presented 5 years ago, and then expands on the new risks especially in multicast scenarios.
As an add-on, discovered implemention security issues in Windows 7/2008, Linux and Cisco will be shown too. Lets hope patches are out until the conference, if not - they had enough time.
All accompanied with GPL'ed tools to and a library: the new thc-ipv6 package. rewritten, expanded, enhanced.</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="2954">vanHauser</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
          <link href="http://events.ccc.de/congress/2005/fahrplan/attachments/642-vh_thcipv6_attackccc05presentation.pdf">slides from 2005 this talk builds on</link>
          <link href="http://www.thc.org/thc-ipv6">the thc-ipv6 attack suite</link>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4125">
        <start>23:00</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 2</room>
        <slug>spinning_the_electornic_wheel</slug>
        <title>Spinning the electronic Wheel</title>
        <subtitle>Still the bicycles for the 21th century</subtitle>
        <track>Making</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>de</language>
        <abstract>3 1/2 Jahre nach dem Talk '21st Century digital Bikes' auf dem Camp 2007 ist einiges in der Welt der elektrischen Fortbewegung passiert. Ende 2010 ist die Gelegenheit den Stand der Dinge aufzurollen, die Neuigkeiten darzustellen und &#252;ber eine, mehr unsch&#228;rfer als klarer, werdende Zukunft der elektrischen Mobilit&#228;t zu sprechen.</abstract>
        <description> 1) Immer noch Fahrzeuge f&#252;r das 21te Jahrhundert, die Freiheit die wir meinen.

Die Auflagen f&#252;r klassische Fahrzeuge steigen stetig. Windschutzscheibe werden mehr und mehr mit amtlichen Aufklebern zugetaped, die Zahl der Regularien und die &#220;berwachung auf verstopften Autobahnen und im urbanen Raum nimmt immer weiter zu. Parallel dazu macht sich eine kleine Nischenbewegung zur voll funktionsf&#228;higen Alternative: E-Bikes - Die momentan wohl angenehmste Form des Individualverkehrs. 

 2) E-Bike / Pedelcs / LEV in der EU

Als E-Biker nimmt man am &#246;ffentlichen Stra&#223;enverkehr teil. Es soll klar gestellt werden, wie elektrisch betriebene Fahrzeuge in der EU rechtlich definiert werden, wann ein elektrisch betriebenes Fahrrad kennzeichenpflichtig ist und wo die T&#252;cken und L&#252;cken der EU-Regulierung liegen.

 3) Technik 

Nach einem &#220;berblick &#252;ber existierende Motortechnik, wird es um b&#252;rstenlose Gleichstrommotoren (brushless DC motors) gehen, welche gewisse aufzuzeigende Vorteile f&#252;r den Einsatz in Fahrzeugen besitzen und au&#223;erdem als Nabenmotoren vor allem f&#252;r Um- und Nachr&#252;stungskonzepte geeignet sind.
Mit dem Microcontroller f&#252;r die Ansteuerung der Motoren und schlie&#223;lich der aktuellen Akkumulatorentechnik soll die Erkl&#228;rung des Antriebsstrang eines modernen E-Bikes komplett gemacht werden.

 4) Zukunft

Kein Orakel sondern unsere W&#252;nsche f&#252;r die Zukunft. Das 21te Jahrhundert l&#228;sst uns noch ein bisschen Luft weiter an der Sache zu Arbeiten - hier unser Aufruf an Interessierte und die Hackergemeinde, wo und wie es weiterhin beim Thema E-Bikes spannend bleibt.
Verbunden mit dem aktuellen Boom-Aufruf der Industrie entsteht das klassische Ungleichgewicht zwischen Marketing befeuerter Massenware und frei dokumentierten bzw. offen entwickelten Systemen und Konzepten. Wir wollen an dieser Stelle Neugierde und Interesse wecken, um im Rahmen von OpenEverything auch bei den E-Bikes weitere Schritte voranzukommen. 



</description>
        <persons>
        </persons>
        <links>
          <link href="http://elektronenrad.de">Projekt elektronenrad</link>
        </links>
      </event>
    </room>
    <room name="Saal 3">
      <event id="4175">
        <start>12:45</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 3</room>
        <slug>from_robot_to_robot</slug>
        <title>From robot to robot</title>
        <subtitle>Restoring creativity in school pupils using robotics</subtitle>
        <track>Society</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language></language>
        <abstract>Today, hacking is reserved for the microscopic fraction of the population who manage to shake themselves free of the suppressive education regime.  Student Robotics is the beginning of the solution.  By fostering creativity through competition to solve engineering challenges, we provide the inspiration society desperately needs.  We develop an open platform for robotics and provide it to schools to open students' minds to the world of hacking.</abstract>
        <description>Student Robotics pushes engineering into schools by running a robotics competition between 16 to 18 year-olds.  We send university students into schools to mentor the participating teams.  The organisation is run entirely by students, who also develop the hardware and software for the participants to use.

Student Robotics involves a whole range of software and hardware development, including including microcontroller programming, computer vision, and web-apps.  This year we've started shipping the BeagleBoard as the robot's main computing device, providing us with a lot of scope for future hacking.

In this talk I will:
 - Discuss the motivation behind Student Robotics
 - Provide a technical overview our current hardware and software
 - Discuss the future of Student Robotics in Europe

Hey Teacher.  Leave them hackers alone.</description>
        <persons>
        </persons>
        <links>
          <link href="http://www.studentrobotics.org">Student Robotics</link>
          <link href="http://www.xgoat.com">My blog</link>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4011">
        <start>14:00</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 3</room>
        <slug>embedded_reverse_engineering</slug>
        <title>JTAG/Serial/FLASH/PCB Embedded Reverse Engineering Tools and Techniques</title>
        <subtitle>a dump of simple tools for embedded analysis at many layers</subtitle>
        <track>Hacking</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>Bring your target. Will release a slew of simple tools that explore attack surfaces and explain of how to use: jtag/serial scanners, parallel flash dumper, DePCB board routing analysis. So, crossover from software RE and start hacking/improving like its 1996 again.</abstract>
        <description>"All non-trivial abstractions, to some degree, are leaky." -- Joel on Software

This applies just as well to hardware. In the soft center of embedded security are the human abstraction layers between embedded developers, pcb designers and asic designers which expose attack surfaces that are often rudimentary and unmovable. 

Using a theoretical embedded target we walk through each surface overcoming obfuscation to gain control. Will release a slew of embedded analysis tools, some lolarduino based, some not. These tools are based on frameworks that support Industrial Design students with electronics prototyping. Meaning, with little technical background you can adapt these tools to your needs.

The audience is invited to bring their target where contributors will be clustered in the hack center and be available to suggest means of protection or application of analysis techniques in your project.

## Tools discussed

*  [Serial Scanner] Arduino based, will scan 30+ pins for a Serial Port at any baudrate. Includes stimulating lines with wakeup signals (\n,etc).
*  [JTAGenum] Arduino based, will scan 30+ pins for a JTAG port. Once found can be used to scan for undocumented instructions and functionality.
*  [Parallel FLASH Dumper] Arduino based, dumps FLASH memory. Flash programmers can be expensive or distribution restricted. Includes discussion for how to dump FLASH where public documentation/footprint cannot be found.
*  [DePCB] (in progress) Given images of PCB layers, can be used to auto-route IC interconnects. Research in-progress. Based on DeGate which does the same at the transistor level of IC's.

## Topics covered

*  Overview of debug surfaces
*  Basic electrical analysis of pins to narrow target scans
*  Using Serial and JTAG scanners
*  Examining undocumented FLASH targets
*  Dumping FLASH
*  Discussion of clues that can be found in PCB design choices</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="2997">Nathan Fain</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
          <link href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/deadhacker/4794404894/">DePCB v0.0 in use. Hopefully by december there will be more target use to show.</link>
          <link href="http://vimeo.com/11699576">Desoldering TSOP FLASH video tutorial</link>
          <link href="http://deadhacker.com/tools/">Code &amp; documentation of tools</link>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4160">
        <start>16:00</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 3</room>
        <slug>automatic_identification_cryptographic_primitives</slug>
        <title>Automatic Identification of Cryptographic Primitives in Software</title>
        <subtitle></subtitle>
        <track>Hacking</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>In this talk I demonstrate our research and the implementation of methods to detect cryptographic algorithms and their parameters in software. Based on
our observations on cryptographic code, I will point out several inherent characteristics to design signature-based and generic identification methods.</abstract>
        <description>Using dynamic binary instrumentation, we record instructions of a program during runtime and create a fine-grained trace. We implement a trace analysis
tool, which also provides methods to reconstruct high-level information from a trace, for example control flow graphs or loops, to detect cryptographic
algorithms and their parameters.

With the results of this work, encrypted data, sent by a malicious program for example, may be decrypted and used by an analyst to gain further insight
on the behavior of the analyzed binary executable. Applications include de-DRM'ing, security auditing, and malware C&amp;C analysis. After the talk we will demonstrate the functionality with a ransomware which uses cryptographic primitives and release the implementation to the public.</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="3103">Felix Gr&#246;bert</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4234">
        <start>17:15</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 3</room>
        <slug>usb_and_libusb</slug>
        <title>USB and libusb for fun and profit</title>
        <subtitle>USB: So much more than a serial port with power</subtitle>
        <track>Making</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>Learn about the benefits and limitations of Universal Serial Bus, how communication works on the bus, how and why the right (and sometimes wrong?) driver can be loaded automatically by the operating system, and find out the easiest way to add USB to your washing machine, toaster, or other favorite appliance.</abstract>
        <description>The talk goes under the hood of the ubiquitous standard and clarifies many concepts that are important to understand when developing firmware or host software for USB devices; host, device, hubs, low speed, full speed, high speed, super speed, using the bus as power supply, cable lengths, all transfer types, endpoints, descriptors and more. The choice between kernel mode or user mode drivers is also discussed, and finally we'll look at how to use libusb; a cross-platform (WinMacLinuxBSD) library for programming USB.</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="2031">Peter Stuge</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4276">
        <start>21:45</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 3</room>
        <slug>a_hackers_introduction_to_cognitive_sciences</slug>
        <title>Cognitive Psychology for Hackers</title>
        <subtitle>Bugs, exploits, and occasional patches</subtitle>
        <track>Science</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>Experience firsthand some of the most interesting, surprising, and perspective-changing findings from cognitive and social neuropsychology. With perceptual illusions, priming, biases, heuristics, and unconscious influences, humans have tons of firmware "bugs". All have exploits; some even have patches.

Learn how to improve your own thinking, use others' bugs to your advantage, and gain new perspective on the unconscious and often illusory processes involved in your perceptions.
</abstract>
        <description>This interactive talk goes through as many interesting, surprising, perspective-changing findings from the cognitive sciences as I can fit in one hour while ensuring that as much as possible has a real, live demonstration that the audience participates in (rather than merely being told about).

It's not just a collection of 'stupid human tricks' (though I'll be using lots of those for examples); this is a coherent narrative about surprising ways in which humans are flawed, how these aren't just things that happen to "other people", and how one might go about improving the situation at least for oneself. Every point will be supported by good science, with references to papers for those who care to read up more about them. 

Come to the meditation workshop afterwards to learn several more interesting and powerful techniques to proactively control your own mindstate.

Tags: #27c3 #cogsci @saizai (emails also appreciated)

See below for blinking disks illusion from Akiyoshi Kitaoka, inspired by Faubert and Herbert (1999). Stop staring at it if it makes you dizzy. No, it's not actually moving - if you point at / fixate on any part of it, that part will remain stable.</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="2622">Sai</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
          <link href="http://www.psy.ritsumei.ac.jp/~akitaoka/classify.html">Akiyoshi Kitaoka's blinking disks illusion</link>
          <link href="http://tinyurl.com/27c3cogsci">Extra feedback appreciated</link>
          <link href="http://saizai.com">Sai's Homepage</link>
        </links>
      </event>
    </room>
  </day>
  <day date="2010-12-28" index="2">
    <room name="Saal 1">
      <event id="4184">
        <start>00:15</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 1</room>
        <slug>stanislaw_lem_weltverbesserer</slug>
        <title>Stanislaw Lem - Der entt&#228;uschte Weltverbesserer</title>
        <subtitle>Ein audiovisuelles Live-Feature</subtitle>
        <track>Culture</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>de</language>
        <abstract>Man kennt ihn als einen der wichtigsten Science-Fiction-Autoren des zwanzigsten Jahrhunderts. Aber Lem war mehr als das: Als Philosoph und Wissenschaftler konnte er technische Entwicklungen der Menschheit und ihre Auswirkungen sogar voraussehen. Als solcher pr&#228;gte er viele heute gel&#228;ufige Begriffe f&#252;r technische Errungenschaften, die seinerzeit noch gar nicht existierten. Seine teils utopische, teils humoristische und selbstironische Art zu schreiben, brachte ihm weltweit gro&#223;e Popularit&#228;t ein, seine B&#252;cher erreichten eine Auflage von mehr als 45 Millionen und wurden zum Teil verfilmt.</abstract>
        <description>Der 1921 in Lemberg im damaligen Polen geborene Schriftsteller blickte im Alter jedoch zunehmend unzufrieden auf sein eigenes Werk wie auch auf die Entwicklung der technisierten Gesellschaften. Er starb 2006 nach l&#228;ngerer Krankheit in Krakau.

Das live gesprochene Feature der H&#246;rspielwerkstatt der Humboldt-Universit&#228;t zu Berlin widmet sich dem Leben und Werk Lems in gewohnter Weise in Wort, Bild und Musik.
</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="1308">Agata Kr&#243;likowski</person>
          <person id="381">Constanze Kurz</person>
          <person id="872">Ina  Kwasniewski</person>
          <person id="411">Jens-Martin Loebel</person>
          <person id="3113">Kai Kittler</person>
          <person id="412">Marcus  Richter</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
          <link href="http://hoerspiel.informatik.hu-berlin.de/">Homepage der H&#246;rspielwerkstatt der Humboldt-Universit&#228;t zu Berlin</link>
          <link href="http://46halbe.org/audio.html">Texte fr&#252;herer Audio-Features</link>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4099">
        <start>11:30</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 1</room>
        <slug>file_print_electronics</slug>
        <title>File -&gt; Print -&gt; Electronics</title>
        <subtitle>A new circuit board printer will liberate you from the Arduino-Industrial Complex</subtitle>
        <track>Making</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>Are you ready to wake up from the cult of Arduino? Tired of plugging together black-box pre-built modules like a mindless drone, copying and pasting in code you found on Hackaday? You've soldered together your TV-Be-Gone, built your fifth Minty Boost, and your bench is awash with discarded Adafruit packaging and Make magazines. It's time to stop this passive consumption. It's time to create something that is truly yours. It's time, my friend, to design your first circuit board. And you'll need a machine to print it.</abstract>
        <description>Outsourcing printed circuit board (PCB) manufacture can be expensive and slow. You want your board now, for free. And designing PCB's is hard. You'll make mistakes, and some boards will be wasted. You can etch your own PCB's at home but the process is fiddly, and notoriously difficult to perfect. What if you had a printer that could make PCB's? A rapid prototyping machine for circuit boards.

In this talk I will present my progress towards an inexpensive PCB printer by reverse engineering Epson inkjet technology. And I'm not talking about the crappy print-and-bake method you might have seen on the internet. Come and learn about the miracle of microfluidics within the modern consumer inkjet printer, and how to push it to do new, exciting things. I'll be describing some reverse engineering techniques, a bit of electronics circuit design and the potential for 3D microfabrication with inkjet technology. 

A PCB will be printed and etched live, on stage, at 27C3!</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="2070">Jeff Gough</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4159">
        <start>12:45</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 1</room>
        <slug>reverse_engineering_mos_6502</slug>
        <title>Reverse Engineering the MOS 6502 CPU</title>
        <subtitle>3510 transistors in 60 minutes</subtitle>
        <track>Hacking</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language></language>
        <abstract>The MOS 6502 CPU, which was designed in 1975 and powered systems like the Apple II, the Atari 2600, the Nintendo NES and the Commodore 64 for two decades, has always been subject to intense reverse engineering of its inner workings. Only recently, the Visual6502.org project has converted a hi-res die-shot of the 6502 into a polygon model suitable for visually simulating the original mask at the transistor level. This talk will present the way from a chip package to a digital representation, how to simulate transistors in software, and new insights gained form this research about 6502 internals, like "illegal" opcodes.
</abstract>
        <description>The presentation only requires a basic understanding of assembly programming and electronics, and is meant to teach, among other things, the methods of efficient and elegant chip design used in the early years of integrated CPUs. The talk consists of three parts. The first part, "6502 from top down", describes the programmer's model, as well as the basic layout of the components of the CPU. In the second part, "6502 from bottom up", we describe how to decap and photograph chips, convert each physical layer of the chip into a polygon model, and how to finally convert this into a network of wires and transistors suitable for logic simulation. The third part, "6502 from the inside out", explains the inner workings of the CPU: how the logic blocks work together, how an instruction is decoded by the PLA ROM into controlling these blocks and busses, and how details like interrupt delivery work. Finally, this information can be used to describe and explain undocumented behaviour, like illegal opcodes and crash instructions, and explain bugs like the BRK/IRQ race, the ROR bug and spurious reads and writes in certain situations.
</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="283">Michael Steil</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
          <link href="http://visual6502.org/JSSim/index.html">The Visual 6502 (JSSim)</link>
          <link href="http://www.pagetable.com/?cat=12">6502 on www.pagetable.com</link>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4143">
        <start>16:00</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 1</room>
        <slug>parttimescientists</slug>
        <title>Part-Time Scientists</title>
        <subtitle>One year of Rocket Science!</subtitle>
        <track>Hacking</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>The Part-Time Scientists is an international team of Scientists and Engineers participating in the first private race to the moon, the Google Lunar X-Prize. Our approach to win this competition is quite unique as everyone involved really is a part-time scientist.

In our presentation we will show our latest lunar rover, lander, electronic and communications developments.
We will show why we used QNX over Linux as our real-time operating system and how are able to manage our team of 70 people scattered all across the world.</abstract>
        <description>The Part-Time Scientists is an international team of Scientists and Engineers participating in the first private race to the moon, the Google Lunar X-Prize. Our approach to win this competition is quite unique as everyone involved really is a part-time scientist.


In our presentation we will show our latest lunar rover, lander, electronic and communications developments.
We will show why we used QNX over Linux as our real-time operating system and how are able to manage our team of 70 people scattered all across the world.

The presentation will feature:
 - our self developed embedded systems
 - how we designed radiation hardened and fault tolerant systems
 - the production of our second Rover generation and their first tests
 - our communication solution ComRay
 - our prototype real world testings
 - what we've done in 2010
 - what we've planning for 2011

and a lot more interesting topics!

Differences to our 26C3 presentation, we will only have 2 speakers.
Our presentation will be focused on actual hardware with a rather short introduction to the topic in general.
</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="3055">Robert Boehme</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
          <link href="http://www.part-time-scientists.com">Part-Time Scientists</link>
          <link href="http://facebook.com/PartTimeScientists">Hell Yeah it's Rocket Science Community</link>
          <link href="http://twitter.com/PTScientists">Part-Time Scientists on Twitter</link>
          <link href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NE7clZDxPHE&amp;hd=1">Promo Video Asimov Jr. 2</link>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4201">
        <start>18:30</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 1</room>
        <slug>the_concert_a_disconcerting_moment_for_free_culture</slug>
        <title>"The Concert"</title>
        <subtitle>a disconcerting moment for free culture</subtitle>
        <track>Culture</track>
        <type>other</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>Corey Cerovsek and Julien Quentin, accomplished musicians known worldwide for their classical recital performances, present something that's not quite an ordinary concert, to draw attention to the importance of the public domain in centuries of classical music tradition. It's both more &#8212; and less &#8212; than what you might expect to see and hear at a classical concert.</abstract>
        <description>Mixing live and recorded music with visuals with a message, Julien Quentin and Corey Cerovsek imagine the heavy curtain of a non-free culture falling on four hundred years of classical music. Ripping and mixing have been going on for longer than you might imagine, and without the Public Domain, much of our classical heritage would be replaced with silence. From Lennon to Bernstein, Bernstein to Mozart, Liszt to Paganini, Sarasate to Bizet, Mendelssohn to Bach, classical music has been a culture of ceaseless sharing in which individuals have nonetheless been able to project indelible voices across the centuries. Had music always been controlled as some would like it to be controlled now, would we have this rich tradition to transmit to you?</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="1170">Alex Antener</person>
          <person id="3121">Corey Cerovsek</person>
          <person id="3124">Julien Quentin</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
          <link href="http://coreycerovsek.com">Corey Cerovsek (Violinist)</link>
          <link href="http://alexantener.com">Alex Antener (Artist Management)</link>
          <link href="http://julienquentin.com">Julien Quentin (Pianist)</link>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4295">
        <start>20:30</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 1</room>
        <slug>high_speed_high_security_cryptography</slug>
        <title>High-speed high-security cryptography: encrypting and authenticating the whole Internet</title>
        <subtitle></subtitle>
        <track>Hacking</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language></language>
        <abstract>Are you writing a program that sends data through the Internet? Are you sending the data through HTTP, or SMTP, or simply TCP, leaving it vulnerable to espionage, corruption, and sabotage by anyone who owns a machine connected to the same network?

You can use SSH and IPsec to protect communication with your own machines, but how do you talk to the rest of the Internet? You can use TCPcrypt to protect yourself against attackers too lazy to forge packets, but how do you protect yourself against serious attackers? You can use HTTPS for low-frequency communication, but how do you handle heavy network traffic, and how do you protect yourself against the security flaws in HTTPS? Today's Internet cryptography is slow, untrustworthy, hard to use, and remarkably unsuccessful as a competitor to good old unprotected TCP.

This talk will present a different approach to high-security Internet cryptography. This approach is easy for users, easy for system administrators, and, perhaps most importantly, easy for programmers. The main reason that the approach has not been tried before is that it seems to involve very slow cryptographic operations; this talk will show that the approach is extremely fast when it is done right.</abstract>
        <description></description>
        <persons>
          <person id="3166">Daniel J. Bernstein</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4061">
        <start>21:45</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 1</room>
        <slug>bulding_custom_disassemblers</slug>
        <title>Building Custom Disassemblers</title>
        <subtitle>Instruction Set Reverse Engineering</subtitle>
        <track>Hacking</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>The Reverse Engineer occasionally faces situations where even his most advanced commercial tools do not support the instruction set of an arcane CPU. To overcome this situation, one can develop the missing disassembler. This talk is meant to be a tutorial on how to approach the task, what to focus on first and what surprises one may be in for. The primary focus will be on the transformation of byte code back into mnemonic representation where only the reverse transformation is available (i.e. you have the respective assembler). It also covers how to integrate your new disassembler into your reverse engineering tool chain.</abstract>
        <description>This tutorial talk will give:
- An introduction to the problem
- How to obtain byte code
- Recognizing basic properties of the byte code
- Finding Addressing Modes
- Implementing a IDA Pro processor module
- Reading code you are not supposed to</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="134">FX of Phenoelit</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4263">
        <start>23:00</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 1</room>
        <slug>the_importance_of_resisting_excessive_government_surveillance</slug>
        <title>The importance of resisting Excessive Government Surveillance</title>
        <subtitle>Join me in exposing and challenging the constant violations of our right to privacy</subtitle>
        <track>Society</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>My name is Nicholas Merrill and I was the plaintiff in a legal case in the US court system where I challenged the FBI&#8217;s policy of using a feature of the so-called USA PATRIOT act - what are called &#8220;National Security Letters&#8221; - to bypass the American Constitution's system of checks and balances and in violation of the United Nations Universal Declaration of Human Rights -  in order to obtain protected personal information and to unmask anonymous Internet users.  I spent over 6 years not able to speak to anyone (other than my lawyers) about my case - forced to lie to those closest to me due to an FBI gag order that carried a possible 10 year prison sentence for violating it.   However the lawsuit resulted in the establishment of two key legal precedents and made changes that affect every Internet worker and Telephone worker in America.    I would like to speak to the 27C3 audience in order to tell about my experience and to challenge (and offer my support and assistance to) those individuals who are in a position to challenge government surveillance requests to follow their consciences and do so.

People who work at Internet Service Providers and Telephone companies as well as IT workers at Universities and private businesses are increasingly likely to encounter government attempts at surveillance.  I would like to speak to the CCC regarding my experiences in resisting a National Security Letter and also a &#8220;Grand Jury Subpoena&#8221; as well as my experience of being gagged by the FBI for nearly 7 years - unable to speak on the subject or identify myself as the plaintiff in the NSL lawsuit.</abstract>
        <description>Nicholas Merrill founded Calyx Internet Access Corporation in 1995. Calyx Internet Access was one of the first commercial Internet service providers operating in New York City.   Calyx pursued relationships with and worked with many activist groups on a pro bono or low-cost basis, including the New York Civil Liberties Union, the Independent Media Center (Indymedia.org) and the Drug Policy Foundation.

In 2004, after a receiving a &#8220;National Security Letter&#8221; from the Federal Bureau of Investigation, and a subsequent request from the U.S. Secret Service, Calyx became involved with the ACLU and in using the legal system and the media to resist illegal government requests for information on Internet users.  For six and a half years, Merrill and the ACLU tirelessly challenged the orders contained in the letter, resulting in the establishment of two key legal precedents overturning aspects of the national security letter program.

Along the way He encountered court proceedings where he could even be present.   Where he could not be referred to by name, but instead was referred to in all court documents as "John Doe" and heavy handed government censorship of court documents under the guise of "National Security" and secret evidence presented to the judge by the FBI that his attorneys were not allowed to see.

The merging of Merrill's long interest in advocacy and free speech combined with his experience with the U.S. government inspired him to form a non-govermental organization (NGO) to deal specifically with this issue without being distracted or compromised by the requirements of a for-profit business.
</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="3156">Nicholas Merrill</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
          <link href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2010/08/09/AR2010080906252.html">Article about my identity being revealed after nearly 7 years of forced anonymity under an FBI gag order</link>
          <link href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/03/22/AR2007032201882.html ">Anonymous op-ed from the washington post from when I was still gagged</link>
          <link href="http://www.wired.com/threatlevel/2010/08/nsl-gag-order-lifted/">Wired magazine story:  " &#8216;John Doe&#8217; Who Fought FBI Spying Freed From Gag Order After 6 Years"</link>
          <link href="http://www.democracynow.org/2010/8/11/gagged_for_6_years_nick_merrill">Democracy now [video]  interview:  " Gagged for 6 Years, Nick Merrill Speaks Out on Landmark Court Struggle Against FBI&#8217;s National Security Letters"</link>
          <link href="http://www.aclu.org/national-security/doe-v-holder">ACLU Archive of documents related to my case</link>
        </links>
      </event>
    </room>
    <room name="Saal 2">
      <event id="4203">
        <start>11:30</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 2</room>
        <slug>distributed_fpga_number_crunching_for_the_masses</slug>
        <title>Distributed FPGA Number Crunching For The Masses</title>
        <subtitle>How we obtained the equivalent power of a Deep Crack for a fistful of dollars - and how the community can benefit from this</subtitle>
        <track>Hacking</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>In 1998, the EFF built "Deep Crack", a machine designed to perform a walk over DES's 56-bit keyspace in nine days, for $250.000. With today's FPGA technology, a cost decrease of 25x can be achieved, as the copacobana project has shown. If that's still too much, two approaches should be considered: Recycling hardware and distributed computing. This talk will be about combining both approaches for the greater good.
</abstract>
        <description>A number of projects ([Copacobana] [1], [Picocomputing] [2]) have shown that with today's technology enough brute force computing power to break limited keylength ciphers (like DES) is affordable even for small companies. But what about Joe Geek at home? Recycling FPGAs is one option ([nsa@home] [3]), distributed computing another ([distributed.net] [4], ...). This project combines both approaches, developing a toolchain that can be used to prototype a project on a low-end FPGA (or even in a free simulator), and then scaling up the effort across different implementations onto a large number of devices. An example client implementation uses an FPGA in a widely available consumer device to provide computing power when the device is in standby. Another approach that will be discussed in detail is how to obtain decommissioned high-end FPGA-based hardware. We will have hardware to show with a live demo!

[1]: http://www.copacobana.org/ "Copacobana"
[2]: http://www.picocomputing.com/pdf/PR_Pico_DES_BH_Jan_29_2010.pdf "Picocomputing"
[3]: http://nsa.unaligned.org/ "nsa@home"
[4]: http://www.distributed.net/Main_Page "distributed.net"
</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="373">Felix Domke</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4210">
        <start>13:00</start>
        <duration>00:30</duration>
        <room>Saal 2</room>
        <slug>lying_to_the_neighbours</slug>
        <title>Lying To The Neighbours</title>
        <subtitle>Fiese Effekte mit tracker-less BitTorrent</subtitle>
        <track>Hacking</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>Distributed Hash Tables implement Routing and Addressability in large P2P networks. In the Kademlia adaption for Bittorrent a peer's address (NodeID) is to be generated randomly, or more appropriate: arbitrarily. Because randomness isn't verifiable, an implementation can advertise itself with popular NodeIDs or even change them on a per-packet basis.</abstract>
        <description>Two issues arise due this design problem:

    Amplification of UDP traffic
    Amplification of TCP traffic

Anyone with a moderate bandwidth connection can induce DDoS attacks with the BitTorrent cloud.

Starting with the prerequisites of BitTorrent, I will outline the importance of tracker-less operation and how Magnet links work. Distributed Hash Tables are explained pertaining to the Kademlia algorithm. It is most interesting how implementations maintain and refresh routing information, allowing a malicious node to become a popular neighbour quickly, and how traffic can be amplified in two ways.

I will present packet rate analysis measured during tests on Amazon EC2.

In conclusion it is explained how the problem of arbitrary NodeIDs can be avoided if the protocol was to be redesigned. A few words are to be given what client authors can do to alleviate the damage potential of the BitTorrent DHT.</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="26">Astro</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4142">
        <start>13:45</start>
        <duration>00:30</duration>
        <room>Saal 2</room>
        <slug>nodejs_as_a_networking_tool</slug>
        <title>Node.js as a networking tool</title>
        <subtitle></subtitle>
        <track>Hacking</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>Node.js is a library that provides non-blocking I/O for Google's V8 JavaScript engine. This talk explores node's suitability for a diverse range of networking applications.</abstract>
        <description>Writing network applications with good concurrency and performance has been a very time consuming task in the past. With the rise of node.js, anybody can now trivially write scalable network applications. This talk explains node's event loop and non-blocking I/O machinery and shows how node may become your tool of choice for future networking adventures. There will also be a look at new threats that could arise from the ability of managing thousands of connections with almost no difficulty.</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="3095">Felix Geisend&#246;rfer</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
          <link href="http://nodejs.org/">The node.js project homepage</link>
          <link href="http://github.com/felixge">My open source contributions on GitHub</link>
          <link href="http://twitter.com/felixge">My twitter profile</link>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4073">
        <start>14:30</start>
        <duration>00:30</duration>
        <room>Saal 2</room>
        <slug>logikschaltungen_ohne_elektronik</slug>
        <title>Logikschaltungen ohne Elektronik</title>
        <subtitle>logische Schaltungen mit Pneumatik</subtitle>
        <track>Making</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language></language>
        <abstract>Ein kurzer &#220;berblick &#252;ber mechanische und str&#246;mungstechnische Logikschaltungen und Computer</abstract>
        <description>In dem Vortrag wollen wir aufzeigen, welche M&#246;glichkeiten es mit pneumatischen und hydraulischen Logikelementen gibt und wo sie fr&#252;her im Einsatz waren und teilweise auch heute noch zu finden sind. Dabei geht es um einfache mechanische Ventile, Folienventilen und Fluidics. Auf die Funktion der einzelnen Logikelemente werden wir nat&#252;rlich eingehen. 

Grunds&#228;tzlich gibt es alle Logikelemente der Elektronik auch als pneumatische/hydraulische Variante. Es soll gekl&#228;rt werden, welche M&#246;glichkeiten es mit solchen Schaltungen gibt, wo die T&#252;cken liegen und wie ich sie mir selbst bauen kann. Es wird auch um aktuelle Beispiele wie Automatisierung in explosionsgef&#228;hrdeten Bereichen, Waschmaschinen, Satelliten oder EMV-Laboren gehen. Selbstverst&#228;ndlich kommen eher exotische Einsatzgebiete wie pneumatische Computer f&#252;r den Einsatz nach einem Atomkrieg oder pneumatisch gesteuerte Raketen nicht zu kurz. Als Exot unter Exoten wird es auch etwas um einen hydraulischen Analogrechner gehen.

</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="3052">&#196;pex</person>
          <person id="3183">xif</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
          <link href="http://www.coats.org/~jack/fluidics/index.htm">Fluidic Grundelemente</link>
          <link href="http://www.blikstein.com/paulo/projects/project_water.html">DIY Fluidics</link>
          <link href="http://www.seanwells.com/water-logic/index.html">low cost logic</link>
          <link href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MONIAC_Computer">MONIAC</link>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4121">
        <start>16:00</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 2</room>
        <slug>is_the_ssliverse_a_safe_place</slug>
        <title>Is the SSLiverse a safe place?</title>
        <subtitle>An update on EFF's SSL Observatory project</subtitle>
        <track>Community</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>The EFF SSL Observatory has collected a dataset of all TLS/HTTPS certificates visible on the public web. We discuss this dataset - what we have learned from it, how you can use it, and how intend to offer a live, continually updated version of it.</abstract>
        <description>TLS/SSL is only as good as your mechanism for verifying the other party, and it turns out that with HTTPS and other CA-certified applications of TLS, that mechanism involves trusting a lot of governments, companies and individuals.

The SSL observatory is a project to bring more transparency to SSL Certificate Authorities, and help understand who really controls the web's cryptographic authentication infrastructure. The Observatory is an Electronic Frontier Foundation (EFF) project that began by surveying port 443 of all public IPv4 space. At Defcon 2010, we reported the initial findings of the SSL Observatory. That included thousands of valid 'localhost' certificates, certificates with weak keys, CA certs sharing keys and with suspicious expiration dates, and the fact that there are approximately 650 organisations that can sign a certificate for any domain that will be trusted by modern desktop browsers, including some that you might regard as untrustworthy.

In this talk we will give an update on new developments in the project, including where to find a copy of our data and how to work with it for your own research; the progress made at fixing some of the vulnerabilities we found; and our design for a new, decentralised version of the SSL Observatory.</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="2508">Jesse</person>
          <person id="1701">Peter Eckersley</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
          <link href="https://eff.org/observatory">EFF's SSL observatory homepage</link>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4123">
        <start>17:15</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 2</room>
        <slug>defense_is_not_dead</slug>
        <title>Defense is not dead</title>
        <subtitle>Why we will have more secure computers - tomorrow</subtitle>
        <track>Hacking</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language></language>
        <abstract>The security model of our current computer architectures - kernel in ring 0, processes in ring 3 - goes back to the early 70s. However, science hasn't stopped.</abstract>
        <description>This talk is going to look into the state of the art in building secure computers, with a focus on type systems and formal verification, and hopefully an outlook on how tomorrow's computers will be more secure than what you can buy now.</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="91">Andreas Bogk</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4195">
        <start>18:30</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 2</room>
        <slug>literarischer_abend</slug>
        <title>Literarischer Abend</title>
        <subtitle></subtitle>
        <track>Community</track>
        <type>podium</type>
        <language>de</language>
        <abstract>Ein literarischer Abend im Quartett.</abstract>
        <description>Anl&#228;&#223;lich einer Diskussion auf intern@ in Vorbereitung der Datenschleuder, Ausgabe 94, im Mai dieses Jahres hatte sich wieder einmal gezeigt, wie wenig Wissen bei vielen Mitgliedern &#252;ber Klassiker der (insbesondere Science-Fiction-)Literatur heutzutage vorhanden ist. Da diese Werke fr&#252;her auch zum inneren Zusammenhalt der Szene beitrugen, auch weil sie gemeinsame Begriffe, Bilder und Visionen aufspannten, auf die als kulturelle Referenz Bezug im politischen Diskurs genommen werden konnte, scheint es angebracht, diese erneut in den Fokus zu r&#252;cken.

Den Rahmen dazu soll eine kurze Einf&#252;hrung bilden, die die Relevanz solcher gemeinsamer Sprache hervorhebt. Sie soll auch aufzeigen, wie Science Fiction es erm&#246;glichte - auch in restriktiveren Rahmenbedingungen - Sozialkritik zu &#228;u&#223;ern. Indem dies in verschl&#252;sselter Form stattfand, transponiert in futuristische Welten, und dem Leser die Aufgabe des Transfers in seine Lebensumst&#228;nde &#252;berlie&#223;, bef&#246;rderte SF dar&#252;berhinaus die F&#228;higkeit der Leserin zur Abstraktion.

Schlie&#223;lich sollen einzelne Autoren und deren bedeutende Werke in Ausz&#252;gen vorgestellt werden und, soweit m&#246;glich, ein Bezug zur aktuellen Situation hergestellt werden. Und au&#223;erdem ist das einfach mal merkw&#252;rdig, wenn Leute nicht wissen, von wem "Pfeif nicht, w&#228;hrend Du pi&#223;t, George, und stell keine Fragen, wenn Du einen geblasen kriegst" stammt. :)

Werke, die bitte vorab zu lesen sind (in keiner bestimmten Reihenfolge):

* Charles Stross, Halting State
* Vernor Vinge, True Names
* John Brunner, The Shockwave Rider und Squares of the City und Am falschen Ende der Zeit und Ein irrer Orbit und eigentlich alles andere auch
* Jeff Noon, Vurt
* Ray Bradbury, Fahrenheit 451
* Stanislaw Lem, Solaris und Der futurologische Kongre&#223;
* William Gibson, Pattern Recognition und Spook Country
* Philip K Dick: Das Orakel vom Berge
* RAW: Cosmic Trigger
* Neal Stephenson: A diamond age</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="7">Andreas Lehner</person>
          <person id="1086">Lars</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
          <link href="http://chaosradio.ccc.de/cre161.html">CRE 161, letztes Drittel zu Literatur</link>
          <link href="http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Das_Literarische_Quartett">"Wir werden &#252;ber B&#252;cher sprechen, und zwar, wie wir immer sprechen: liebevoll und etwas gemein, g&#252;tig und vielleicht ein bisschen b&#246;sartig, aber auf jeden Fall sehr klar und deutlich."</link>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4057">
        <start>21:45</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 2</room>
        <slug>adventures_in_mapping_afghanistan_elections</slug>
        <title>Adventures in Mapping Afghanistan Elections</title>
        <subtitle>The story of 3 Ushahidi mapping and reporting projects.</subtitle>
        <track>Society</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>Monitoring and reporting about elections in a war zone is a complex and dangerous task.  While crisis mapping carried out via sms and email proved highly successful with the use of Ushahidi in situations like post-election violence in Kenya, tracking crime in Atlanta, or earthquake recovery in Haiti, could it prove useful in such a complex situation as the Afghan political process?  This year a team of people set out to do just that with three different Ushahidi mapping projects for national media, national election observers, and international observers.  The following presentation is about the challenges we faced, successes we did or did not have, and the lessons learned for the future of crisis mapping.</abstract>
        <description>In 2008 an open source mapping system called Ushahidi was put into public use for the first time in history. The occasion was a constitutional referendum in Kenya and the goal of the Ushahidi system was to map and track reports of violence throughout the country in the days following the vote.  Through the use of sms reports from the general public, which were then categorized and published on an interactive map accessible on the internet, anyone anywhere in the world could not only get reports about what was happening, they could get almost real time reports about where violence was happening, when, and details regarding those incidents.  

The response in Kenya was so large and the attention the site got was so wide spread, Ushahidi would soon be used to map not only violence surrounding an election, but also earthquake recovery, snow storm recovery, forest fire prevention, crime data in urban environments, and elections monitoring. In each of these situations, the power of crowd-sourcing and interactive mapping via simple sms and email technology was all that was needed to get a body of information no media or government organization could compete with.

In the summer of 2010, on the eve of Parliamentary elections in Afghanistan, several organizations interested in monitoring what happens at the polls and after the votes are in became interested in whether or not Ushahidi could be useful for their purposes. The Afghan Press agency, Pajwhok, as well as the national elections observer organization (FEFA) and the international elections observers (Democracy International) all sought to implement some form of Ushahidi system for their observers. They approached my organization, Small World News (SWN) that has assisted in Ushahidi projects in the past, to carry out this task.

Over the course of just over 1 month, these three systems were rolled out in different ways, with varying level of restrictions due to security and other institutional regulations. The result tells three different stories about how the election went, while also providing a list of lessons about what open source interactive mapping can provide (or not provide) for a nation like Afghanistan with such a specific list of problems.

The presentation is an explanation of both the process and the lessons learned.</description>
        <persons>
        </persons>
        <links>
          <link href="http://umap.afghan2010.com">Ushahidi System Built for Internatinal Elections Observers Democracy International</link>
          <link href="http://aliveinafghanistan.org">Mapping reports from reporters throughout afghanistan as well as elections monitors.</link>
          <link href="http://www.fefa2010.com/">Free and Fair Elections Afghanistan Map</link>
          <link href="http://">http://</link>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4138">
        <start>23:00</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 2</room>
        <slug>secure_communications_below_the_hearing_threshold</slug>
        <title>Secure communications below the hearing threshold</title>
        <subtitle>Improved approaches for auditive steganography</subtitle>
        <track>Hacking</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>Auditive steganography allows for various usage scenarios. In our project we focused on hidden communications in VoIP and GSM in which voice data is typically compressed and transmitted in realtime. A framework has been developed to meet these requirements, providing interfaces for robust steganographic algorithms.</abstract>
        <description>The need for steganography has arisen from scenarios that forbid the application of cryptographic algorithms for secure communications. Countries that made secret message exchange a delict are an example for 
such scenarios. The LSB algorithm used by many open- and closed-source projects is insecure, as its application can be statistically detected. Therefore, we focused on alternate approaches which are more robust against operations on the bit-level, such as compression, D/A-, A/D-conversion and channel idiosyncrasies, such as spread spectrum steganography in time and frequency domain.

Secure and hidden communications demand more than an embedding algorithm. Involved elements include:
* protocols for data flow handling,
* various embedding algorithms and
* support for different I/O-interfaces.

For correct interaction of these elements, arranging them in a layered model is a reasonable approach for the distribution of the required tasks such as frame and packet building, checksumming, transmission, etc. From this model we derived our software architecture which is portable to common platforms (Linux/Unix, Windows, ...) and various architectures (x86_32, x86_64, mips). 

This talk gives an introduction to the topic and describes the development and implementation of our framework based on a novel layered model for auditive steganography including a live demonstration.</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="3085">Marcus Nutzinger</person>
          <person id="3057">Rainer Poisel</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
          <link href="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/xpls/abs_all.jsp?arnumber=5555319">Paper: Software architecture for real-time steganography in auditive media</link>
        </links>
      </event>
    </room>
    <room name="Saal 3">
      <event id="4081">
        <start>11:30</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 3</room>
        <slug>netzmedienrecht_lobbyismus_korruption</slug>
        <title>Netzmedienrecht, Lobbyismus und Korruption</title>
        <subtitle>Wie wirkt die Lobby von Medienkonzernen?</subtitle>
        <track>Society</track>
        <type>workshop</type>
        <language>de</language>
        <abstract>Die Mediennutzung, aber auch ihre Verwaltung und Verg&#252;tung, also ihr Management, m&#252;ssen an eine digitale Netzwelt angepasst werden. Wie ist der Stand der juristischen Auseinandersetzung um die Rechte von Urhebern, Verwertern und Nutzern von Medieninhalten? Wie und wo setzen sich starke Wirtschaftsinteressen mit Lobbygruppen durch?</abstract>
        <description>Hintergrund sind entsprechende Debatten in internationalen Organisationen, z. B. TRIPS (Trade Related Aspects of Intellectual Property) und WIPO (World Intellectual Property Organization) sowie das von der EU lancierte Gr&#252;nbuch &#8218;Urheberrechte in der wissensbestimmten Wirtschaft&#8216; (2008). Dort wurde eine &#8222;Ausgewogenheit der Interessen von Urhebern und Nutzern von geistigen Produkten bzw. Wissensobjekten&#8220; proklamiert, die sich leider so nicht erkennen l&#228;sst. Im Gr&#252;nbuch ist eine Tendenz erkennbar, die L&#246;sung der Problematik der urheberrechtlich gebremsten Verbreitung von Wissen von der Verschiebung auf das Gebiet des Vertragsrechts zu erwarten. Dies erweckt den Verdacht, dass sich hier die Lobby der Medienindustrie durchgesetzt haben k&#246;nnte, die dank ihrer Rechtsabteilungen von besagter Tendenz profitieren d&#252;rfte &#8211; gegen&#252;ber Bildung und Forschung, aber auch generell gegen&#252;ber den Urhebern ihrer Inhalte.

Rechtlich entscheidend sind dabei die Ausnahmen und Beschr&#228;nkungen kommerzieller Verwertungsrechte, im UHG kodifiziert f&#252;r 1. Behinderte, 2. Archive/Museen etc., 3. Bildung/Forschung sowie &#8222;evtl. noch zu schaffende&#8220; f&#252;r von Nutzern geschaffene Inhalte: v. a. Open Source, Wikis etc.
 </description>
        <persons>
          <person id="3059">Thomas Barth</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4296">
        <start>12:45</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 3</room>
        <slug>lightning_days_d2</slug>
        <title>Lightning Talks - Day 2</title>
        <subtitle>4 minutes of fame</subtitle>
        <track>Community</track>
        <type>lightning</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>4 minutes for every speaker. Learn about the good, the bad, and the ugly - in software, hardware, projects, and more.</abstract>
        <description>Give a lightning fast talk about your favourite project, program, system - and thereby find people with the same interest to proceed and promote it. Alternatively - give us a good rant about something and give us some good reasons why it should die. ;)

Get right at it, don't waste time by explaining too much, get the main points across, and then let us know how to contact you on the congress for a talk!

Whatever you do - please practise it, and don't be boring. Or else. You have been warned! :-P</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="1476">Nick Farr</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4149">
        <start>14:00</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 3</room>
        <slug>i_control_your_code</slug>
        <title>I Control Your Code</title>
        <subtitle>Attack Vectors Through the Eyes of Software-based Fault Isolation</subtitle>
        <track>Hacking</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language></language>
        <abstract>Unsafe languages and an arms race for new bugs calls for an additional line of
defense in software systems. User-space virtualization uses dynamic
instrumentation to detect different attack vectors and protects from the
execution of malicious code. An additional advantage of these virtualization
systems is that they can be used to analyze different exploits step by step and
to extract the exploit code from a running program.

This talk explains the concept of different attack vectors (stack buffer
overflows, format string attacks, return to libc attacks, race attacks /
TOCTTOU, integer overflows, heap buffer overflows, and code anomalies). For each
of these attack vectors we show possible exploits and explain how the
virtualization system is able to detect and prevent the exploit.</abstract>
        <description>User-space virtualization uses a binary translation framework to instrument all
running code. The instrumentation works like an additional virtualization layer
and makes it possible to observe any changes to the runtime datastructures (code
and data) of a running program. We use fastBT to instrument and analyze
different exploitable programs. The added instrumentation detects changes in
runtime layout and stops the program whenever exploit code is about to be
executed.

This talk presents different classes of exploits that can be observed in a
dynamic instrumentation system. The exploits are analyzed and different security
strategies are discussed. We then show how the instrumentation framework can
implement an online protection mechanism against each class of attack vectors.

Observable Attack Vectors
- Stack Overflow
  A limited buffer is (over) flown with user-data and over writes data on the
  stack (e.g., the return instruction pointer).
- Format String Attack
  An attack can write to an arbitrary address (e.g., the return instruction
  pointer or the address of a library function) if unvalidated user input is
  passed directly to the printf function.
- Return to libc Attack
  This attack prepares multiple stack frames that execute code sequences in
  libraries. The stack frame can be constructed so that (almost) arbitrary code
  is executed.
- Race Attacks / TOCTTOU
  Time-of-check-to-time-of-use race conditions exploit the fact that they can
  change values on the stack after they are checked but before they are used in
  the program or kernel.
- Integer Overflow
  Overflows can be triggered by using a negative integer value instead of an
  unsigned value.
- Heap Overflow
  A heap buffer overflow is used to overwrite function pointers or data from the
  memory allocator to trigger execution of arbitrary code.
- Code Anomalies
  x86_64 code is backward compatible to ia32 and in modern operating systems
  x86_64 and ia32 code can be mixed. The mix of different system calls makes it
  possible to break out of sand boxes that are not aware of all possible
  combinations of system calls.

The exploits are detected generally whenever the program branches to the
injected code or to the constructed code fragments. The program is interrupted
and a debugger can be attached to analyze the state of the program. TOCTTOU
attacks can be detected by observing the threads and using a specific system
call architecture.

Conclusion
Dynamic instrumentation is an important tool to prohibit, detect, and analyze
different attack vectors to running programs. Additional instrumentation guards
can be used to better understand exploits. The additional layer of
virtualization implemented through dynamic instrumentation can be used to detect
and log bugs and is an additional line of defense against new exploits.

Related Work
A detailed discussion of related work is in the paper. These references here are
for informational purposes only (to show how this talk was inspired) and not
complete.
- fastBT: A fast binary translator that enables different security extensions.
  http://nebelwelt.net/fastBT
- 26c3 talk: Hacking the Hackers (user space virtualization and encapsulation
  mixed with system call authorization to prevent exploits)
- Watson, R. N. "Exploiting Concurrency Vulnerabilities in System Call Wrappers"
- Levy, Elias. "Smashing the stack for fun and profit"
- c0ntex. "Bypassing non-executable-stack during exploitation using
  return-to-libc"
- Shacham, Hovav; Page, Matthew; Pfaff, Ben; Goh, Eu-Jin; Modadugu, Nagendra;
  and Boneh, Dan. "On the Effectiveness of Address-Space Randomization"
- Borisov, Nikita; Johnson, Rob; Sastry, Naveen; and Wagner, David; 2005;
  "Fixing Races for Fun and Profit: How to abuse atime"
- Phrack #60, Basic Integer Overflows
- Seccomp vulnerabilities due to x86_64 and ia32 compatibility issues:
  http://scarybeastsecurity.blogspot.com/2009/02/linux-kernel-minor-seccomp.html
</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="2574">Mathias Payer</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
          <link href="http://nebelwelt.net/fastBT">fastBT: Binary Instrumentation System</link>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4144">
        <start>16:00</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 3</room>
        <slug>short_political_history_of_acoustics</slug>
        <title>A short political history of acoustics</title>
        <subtitle>For whom, and to do what, the science of sound was developed in the 17th century</subtitle>
        <track>Society</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language></language>
        <abstract>The birth of the modern science of acoustics was directly intertwined with the desires to surveill and communicate, either in secret or to everybody at once. Acoustics was not just about 'learning more about nature,' right from the start it was an applied science, driven by very clear notions of who has the right, and thus should have the possibility, of listening in on others, who needs to be able to converse in private, and who should be heard by everybody if he wishes to. How are these historical ideas related to those of today?</abstract>
        <description>The talk teases out these juicy implications from mostly original source material, focussing on the strange figure of the Jesuit Athanasius Kircher, but also looking at better known characters of the Scientific Revolution like Francis Bacon, Marin Mersenne, and the early Royal Society. There are plenty of phantastic 'scientific' illustrations to look at as well as descriptions of devices (for the amplification of sound, for acoustical surveillance, entertainment, and the so called 'cryptoacoustics') that did or rather did not work to laugh about, but the key questions are those about power and its relationship to notions of privacy and communication, the history of privacy as a privilege and surveillance as a 'right' of government. Some of these ideas become especially clear in the phantasies they produced. How are these historical ideas related to our own about who gets to listen in, who gets to converse in private, and who get to be heard by everybody? And what has all that to do with the history of science, and even magic?</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="664">Oona Leganovic</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4067">
        <start>17:15</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 3</room>
        <slug>data_analysis_in_terabit_ethernet_traffic</slug>
        <title>Data Analysis in Terabit Ethernet Traffic</title>
        <subtitle>Solutions for monitoring and lawful interception within a lot of bits</subtitle>
        <track>Hacking</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>Network traffic grows faster than monitoring and analysis tools can handle. During the last two years a couple of appliances hit the market which help in finding the &#8220;bits of interest&#8221;. Recently installed strategies and solutions for carriers, banks or lawful interception organizations will be discussed as examples.</abstract>
        <description>Quite every laptop nowadays is capable of handling Gigabit traffic. But doing a network analysis will hit the boundaries of CPU load quite quickly. Now, with 10GbE lines as the usual speed of carrier's and company's backbone, traffic monitoring and analysis became more and more painful. Even the biggest and most expensive analysis appliances on the market are barely capable of a real time traffic monitoring for more than 8Gbit/s.

That's were a couple of vendors showed up and created devices which can handle multiple 10GbE lines at the same time. They call them &#8220;Active Distributed Traffic Capture Systems&#8221; or &#8220;Intelligent Data Access Networking Switches&#8221; &#8211; in short &#8220;Data Access Systems&#8221;. The primary use is for the aggregation and distribution of traffic. But all of the Data Access Systems are also capable of filtering traffic with the help of FPGA or CPLD techniques. So a carrier, bank or lawful interception organization can aggregate the data from many physical lines into one Data Access System, enter some filters with the help of a browser GUI, and distribute the resulting traffic to the analysis machines. It's easy to monitor 100 lines of 10GbE traffic.

For competitive reasons, those vendors started to invent new features for a better or easier analysis of the data on the analysis devices. These include ingress port tagging, time stamping with nanosecond accuracy, slicing of packets and recalculation of checksums in realtime, blanking bits in packets, or even layer 7 filtering for e-mail and instant messenger addresses with full flow capturing.

The interesting part for the usage is to create an infrastructure where even without data retention and a long term analysis specific users or just their communication with possible &#8221;interesting&#8220; data for intelligence agencies can be triggered and captured in real time. So, the process of the analysis can be quickened to quite no time. It's safe to say, that the flagship appliance by a vendor has been designed by request of US intelligence agencies.

Of course, those devices have to be managed by administrators. For the ease of usage every vendor moved from a CLI based configuration interface to a shiny web GUI &#8211; with a couple of flaws. It is easy to break into the system or read out the configuration without access.

This lecture will discuss the possibilities of today's data analysis with the help of these Data Access Systems. An overview of the features will help to understand that data analysis devices are not anymore the limiting factor in deep packet inspection of a huge amount of traffic. Examples will show what already has been set up and what is possible by companies and organizations &#8211; and which traffic they might monitor yet.

During the last three years the speaker installed those appliances from different vendors at customers across Europe, gained deep knowledge of their usage, established a strong contact to the technicians and chief officers both at the vendors and customers side, and found out a lot about the hardware and software by reverse engineering.</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="18">Lars Weiler</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4097">
        <start>18:30</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 3</room>
        <slug>identifizierung_von_netzwerkprotokollen</slug>
        <title>Techniken zur Identifizierung von Netzwerk-Protokollen</title>
        <subtitle></subtitle>
        <track>Science</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>de</language>
        <abstract>Der Vortrag soll Techniken aufzeigen, mit denen man Netzwerk-Protokolle identifizieren kann, die in Layer 7 des OSI-Modells angesiedelt sind. Alle Techniken - darunter auch die Deep Packet Inspection (DPI) - werden technisch erl&#228;utert und kritisch bewertet.
</abstract>
        <description>Der Fokus des Vortrags liegt auf dem SPID-Algorithmus, den Hjelmvik und John entwickelten. Dieser Algorithmus inspiziert die Netzwerk-Protokolle mit statistischen Merkmalen. Die Ergebnisse der statistischen Analyse geben Aufschluss, wie man Protocol Obfuscation in Zukunft verbessern kann, um zu verhindern das Protokolle erkannt werden.

Auf die folgenden Techniken zur Identifizierung von Netzwerk-Protokollen wird inhaltlich eingangen: Port-Nummern, Deep-Packet-Inspection, Maschinen-Lern-Algorithmen und der hybride Ansatz SPID. Alle Techniken werden nach den folgenden Anforderungen abgewogen. Erstens sollen Protokolle in naher Echtzeit erkannt werden. Zweitens soll eine m&#246;glichst robuste und sichere Erkennung von Protokollen m&#246;glich sein. Und Drittens soll die Technik auf leistungsarmer und kosteng&#252;nstiger Hardware laufen.

Nach der Abw&#228;gung werden die technischen Einzelheiten des SPID-Algorithmus erl&#228;utert und ausgew&#228;hlte statistische Merkmale beleuchtet. Diese bilden nachfolgend die Grundlage, um Protocol Obfuscation zu verbessern. Abschlie&#223;end werden verschiedene Evaluierungs-Ergebnisse pr&#228;sentiert.</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="2963">Florian Adamsky</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
          <link href="http://sourceforge.net/apps/mediawiki/spid/index.php?title=Main_Page">Spid Wiki</link>
          <link href="http://www.iis.se/docs/The_SPID_Algorithm_-_Statistical_Protocol_IDentification.pdf">The SPID Algorithm Statistical Protocol IDentification </link>
          <link href="http://spid.sourceforge.net/sncnw09-hjelmvik_john-CR.pdf">Paper: SPID</link>
          <link href="http://alpha.fh-friedberg.de/iem/fileadmin/user_upload/jaeger/PID1034610.pdf">Enhancements to Statistical Protocol IDentification (SPID) for Self-Organised QoS in LANs </link>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4087">
        <start>21:45</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 3</room>
        <slug>console_hacking_2010</slug>
        <title>Console Hacking 2010</title>
        <subtitle>PS3 Epic Fail</subtitle>
        <track>Hacking</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>Over 70 million Wiis, over 40 million Xbox 360s and over 35 million Playstation 3s have been sold in the last few years. That makes over 145 million embedded devices out there and most of them are just used to play games. But what can you do with them if you don't like playing games? You hack them to make them run your own code of course! 
We're going to talk about the various hacks that you can use to gain control of your hardware and make it do what you want it to do.</abstract>
        <description>2010 saw the first hacks for the Playstation 3, soon after Sony removed Other OS functionality. We will detail the operation of current PS3 exploits, show a few new ones and explain where and how Sony went wrong when designing its security system, and show how these holes can be used to gain control over the system and bring Linux back to the PS3.

We will also go over hacks for the other consoles, including the JTAG hack for the Xbox 360 which made running homebrew code more convenient, and the cat-and-mouse games that Nintendo played with us to combat Wii hacks. We might also check out the security of their 'new' handheld console - the DSi.

Gamers might find this talk interesting even though it is targeted at those who hack (or design) embedded system security. A basic knowledge of crypto is therefore assumed.
We will also be present in the Hackcenter before and after the presentation for those of you who are interested in learning more about the subject.</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="2050">bushing</person>
          <person id="2134">marcan</person>
          <person id="3049">sven</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
          <link href="http://hackmii.com">HackMii</link>
          <link href="http://wiibrew.org">Wii Wiki</link>
          <link href="http://dsibrew.org">DSi Wiki</link>
          <link href="http://free60.org">Free60 Wiki</link>
        </links>
      </event>
    </room>
  </day>
  <day date="2010-12-29" index="3">
    <room name="Saal 1">
      <event id="4298">
        <start>11:30</start>
        <duration>02:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 1</room>
        <slug>ccc_jahresrueckblick_2010</slug>
        <title>CCC-Jahresr&#252;ckblick 2010</title>
        <subtitle></subtitle>
        <track>Community</track>
        <type>podium</type>
        <language>de</language>
        <abstract>Wir berichten &#252;ber vergangene Veranstaltungen, Erfa-Aktivit&#228;ten, Demonstrationen, Hacks, Medienkontakte, Gerichtsverhandlungen, Lobbyarbeit sowie weiteres Erfreuliches und &#196;rgerliches des Jahres 2010 keinesfalls objektiv, sondern mit der gewohnten Hackerperspektive.</abstract>
        <description>Wir berichten &#252;ber vergangene Veranstaltungen, Erfa-Aktivit&#228;ten, Demonstrationen, Hacks, Medienkontakte, Gerichtsverhandlungen, Lobbyarbeit sowie weiteres Erfreuliches und &#196;rgerliches des Jahres 2010 keinesfalls objektiv, sondern mit der gewohnten Hackerperspektive.</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="91">Andreas Bogk</person>
          <person id="45">Andy M&#252;ller-Maguhn</person>
          <person id="381">Constanze Kurz</person>
          <person id="9">Frank Rieger</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4094">
        <start>17:15</start>
        <duration>02:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 1</room>
        <slug>netzneutralitaet_und_qos</slug>
        <title>Netzneutralit&#228;t und QoS - ein Widerspruch?</title>
        <subtitle>Fakten auf den Tisch</subtitle>
        <track>Society</track>
        <type>podium</type>
        <language>de</language>
        <abstract>Geht es mit der Netzneutralit&#228;t zu Ende? Was wir den Lobbyisten und PR-Leuten der Telekommunikationsunternehmen argumentativ entgegenzusetzen? Was sind die Fakten, was geh&#246;rt ins Reich der Mythen?</abstract>
        <description>Tim Berners-Lee hat folgende griffige Definition der Netzneutralit&#228;t gefunden: "Net neutrality is this: If I pay to connect to the Net with a certain quality of service, and you pay to connect with that or greater quality of service, then we can communicate at that level."

Doch welche der sagenumwobenen Kapazit&#228;tsengp&#228;sse existieren wirklich? Und wie soll Quality of Service (QoS) praktisch in Zukunft gehandhabt werden? Was ist machbar, was sind die Bedingungen f&#252;r eine gesetzliche Regulierung? Fragen &#252;ber Fragen, die mit Euch zusammen diskutiert werden sollen.</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="1252">Alexander Morlang</person>
          <person id="91">Andreas Bogk</person>
          <person id="1755">Markus Beckedahl</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4211">
        <start>20:30</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 1</room>
        <slug>chip_and_pin_is_broken</slug>
        <title>Chip and PIN is Broken</title>
        <subtitle>Vulnerabilities in the EMV Protocol</subtitle>
        <track>Hacking</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>EMV is the dominant protocol used for smart card payments worldwide, with over 730 million cards in circulation. Known to bank customers as &#8220;Chip and PIN&#8221;, it is used in Europe; it is being introduced in Canada; and there is pressure from banks to introduce it in the USA too. EMV secures credit and debit card transactions by authenticating both the card and the customer presenting it through a combination of cryptographic authentication codes, digital signatures, and the entry of a PIN. In this paper we describe and demonstrate a protocol flaw which allows criminals to use a genuine card to make a payment without knowing the card&#8217;s PIN, and to remain undetected even when the merchant has an online connection to the banking network.</abstract>
        <description> The fraudster performs a man-in-the-middle attack to trick the terminal into believing the PIN verified correctly, while telling the issuing bank that no PIN was entered at all. The paper considers how the flaws arose, why they remained unknown despite EMV&#8217;s wide deployment for the best part of a decade, and how they might be fixed. Because we have found and validated a practical attack against the core functionality of EMV, we conclude that the protocol is broken. This failure is significant in the field of protocol design, and also has important public policy implications, in light of growing reports of fraud on stolen EMV cards. Frequently, banks deny such fraud victims a refund, asserting that a card cannot be used without the correct PIN, and concluding that the customer must be grossly negligent or lying. Our attack can explain a number of these cases, and exposes the need for further research to bridge the gap between the theoretical and practical security of bank payment systems.

Smart cards have gradually replaced magnetic strip cards for point-of-sale and
ATM transactions in many countries.  The leading system, EMV (named after
Europay, MasterCard, and Visa), has been deployed throughout most of Europe,
and is currently being rolled out in Canada. As of early 2008, there were over
730 million EMV compliant smart cards in circulation worldwide. In EMV,
customers authorize a credit or debit card transaction by inserting their card
and entering a PIN into a point-of-sale terminal; the PIN is typically verified
by the smart card chip, which is in turn authenticated to the terminal by a
digital certificate. The transaction details are also authenticated by a
cryptographic message authentication code (MAC), using a symmetric key shared
between the payment card and the bank that issued the card to the customer (the
issuer).  EMV was heavily promoted under the &#8220;Chip and PIN&#8221; brand during its
national rollout in the UK. The technology was advertised as a solution to
increasing card fraud: a chip to prevent card counterfeiting, and a PIN to
prevent abuse of stolen cards. Since its introduction in the UK the fraud
landscape has changed significantly: lost and stolen card fraud is down, and
counterfeit card fraud experienced a two year lull. But no type of fraud has
been eliminated, and the overall fraud levels have actually risen (see Figure
1). The likely explanation for this is that EMV has simply moved fraud, not
eliminated it.  One goal of EMV was to externalise the costs of dispute from
the issuing bank, in that if a disputed transaction has been authorised by a
manuscript signature, it would be charged to the merchant, while if it had been
authorised by a PIN then it would be charged to the customer. The net effect is
that the banking industry, which was responsible for the design of the system,
carries less liability for the fraud. The industry describes this as a
&#8216;liability shift&#8217;.  In the past few years, the UK media have reported numerous
cases where cardholders&#8217; complaints have been rejected by their bank and by
government-approved mediators such as the Financial Ombudsman Service, using
stock excuses such as &#8216;Your card was CHIP read and a PIN was used so you must
have been negligent.&#8217; Interestingly, an increasing number of complaints from
believable witnesses indicate that their EMV cards were fraudulently used
shortly after being stolen, despite there having been no possibility that the
thief could have learned the PIN.  In this paper, we describe a potential
explanation. We have demonstrated how criminals can use stolen &#8220;Chip and PIN&#8221;
(EMV) smart cards without knowing the PIN. Since &#8220;verified by PIN&#8221; &#8211; the
essence of the system &#8211; does not work, we declare the Chip and PIN system to be
broken.</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="143">Steven J. Murdoch</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
          <link href="http://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/research/security/banking/nopin/">further details</link>
          <link href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1pMuV2o4Lrw">video</link>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4070">
        <start>21:45</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 1</room>
        <slug>fnord_jahresrueckblick</slug>
        <title>Fnord-Jahresr&#252;ckblick 2010</title>
        <subtitle>von Atomausstieg bis Zwangsintegration</subtitle>
        <track>Society</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language></language>
        <abstract>Auch dieses Jahr werden wir uns wieder bem&#252;hen, Euch mit einem R&#252;ckblick auf die Fnords des Jahres zu unterhalten.</abstract>
        <description>Im Format einer lockeren Abendshow werden wir die Highlights des Jahres pr&#228;sentieren, die Meldungen zwischen den Meldungen, die subtilen Sensationen hinter den Schlagzeilen. Kommen Sie, h&#246;ren Sie, sehen Sie! Lassen Sie sich mitrei&#223;en!</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="1046">Felix von Leitner</person>
          <person id="9">Frank Rieger</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4141">
        <start>23:00</start>
        <duration>02:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 1</room>
        <slug>hacker_jeopardy</slug>
        <title>Hacker Jeopardy</title>
        <subtitle>Number guessing for geeks</subtitle>
        <track>Community</track>
        <type>contest</type>
        <language>de</language>
        <abstract>The Hacker Jeopardy is a quiz show.</abstract>
        <description>The well known reversed quiz format, but of course hacker style. It once was entitled "number guessing for geeks" by a German publisher, which of course is an unfair simplification. It's also guessing of letters and special characters. ;)

Three initial rounds will be played, the winners will compete with each other in the final.
</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="933">Ray</person>
          <person id="101">Stefan 'Sec' Zehl</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
    </room>
    <room name="Saal 2">
      <event id="4244">
        <start>11:30</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 2</room>
        <slug>critical_overview_of_10_years_pet</slug>
        <title>A Critical Overview of 10 years of Privacy Enhancing Technologies</title>
        <subtitle></subtitle>
        <track>Society</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>The objective of the session is to provide a critical overview of "privacy research" within computer science. The mechanisms proposed in the last ten year include mechanisms for anonymous communications, censorship resistance, selective disclosure credentials (and their integration in identity management systems), as well as privacy in databases. All of these system are meant to shield the user from different aspects of on-line surveillance either through allowing a user to keep some of her data "confidential" or by allowing her to assert "control" over her data. We will illustrate using concrete examples, why some paradigms came to dominate the &#64257;eld, their advantages, but also their blind spots, and unfulfilled promises given the conditions of our surveillance societies.</abstract>
        <description>Since 2000 there has been a renewed interest amongst computer scientists in the &#64257;eld of &#8221;privacy technology&#8221;. This includes mechanisms for &#8220;anonymous&#8221; communications, censorship resistance, selective disclosure credentials, as well as privacy in databases - all of which are meant to shield the user from some aspects of on-line surveillance. Beyond the lab, some of those systems have been deployed and are widely used today. 

Yet, the type of surveillance against which privacy technologies are supposed to offer protection is often ill-de&#64257;ned, and widely varying between works: from an individual who wishes &#8220;to hide an occasional purchase from his spouse&#8221;, to &#8220;groups coordinating political dissent under totalitarian regimes&#8221;. While privacy is seen as the key unifying theme of these works only one aspect of it is systematically represented, namely &#8221;con&#64257;dentiality&#8221;. Privacy as self-de&#64257;nition, informational self-determination or as a public good that needs to be negotiated is often neglected. Further, the increasing omni-presence of surveillance technologies, the informatisation of every day life, as well as active resistance to on-line surveillance are used as justifying departure points for privacy technologies but they have so far not been explored in depth in the privacy research &#64257;eld. 

In this talk, we explore the development of contemporary privacy technologies, its key results and methodologies. At its heart our argument is that the &#64257;eld of privacy technology was seeded by computer security and cryptography experts that rushed to apply their tools to new problems, yielding mixed results. Additional pressures from different stakeholders to devise technology that will make large IT systems acceptable to the public has led to further confusion about the goals and methods most appropriate to embed privacy friendly values into computer systems. Further, the recent trend has been to replace the confidentiality paradigm with what can be called the "control" paradigm. Using concrete examples, we seek to explain why some paradigms came to dominate the &#64257;eld, their advantages, but  also their blind spots, and unfulfilled promises.</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="3147">seda</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4046">
        <start>13:00</start>
        <duration>00:30</duration>
        <room>Saal 2</room>
        <slug>all_colours_are_beautiful</slug>
        <title>AllColoursAreBeautiful</title>
        <subtitle>interactive light installation inspired by blinkenlights</subtitle>
        <track>Community</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language></language>
        <abstract>Starting in the beginning of August 2010 and lasting until the mid of November, the project AllColoursAreBeautiful by the Munich chapter of the Chaos Computer Club was serving as a platform for interested people on the world to illuminate, animate and interact with the front of a vacant department store in Munich.</abstract>
        <description>The windows were illuminated by remotely controllable, networked RGB LEDs in colorfully light the facade. A web editor was developed to ease the creation of animations at home or in front of the building with a laptop or mobile phone. Furthermore, animations could be put in a queue by sending a simple text message (SMS). Running animations could be viewed with a client program or by a webcam stream. Over 400 animations were created by the public. Next year another, bigger installation in Munich is planned.

The purpose of our talk is to outline the infrastructure we built for this project and inspire other hackers to use it for rolling their own installation in their hometown. We will explain our open hardware and software design in the background and talk about our rationale behind our design decisions and comment on possible improvements in future iterations. We won't forget to include the biggest fails, fnords and pitfalls concering funding, authorizations and communication.

At the Congress we will rebuild our installation using boxes. Interested hackers are very welcome to play with this colorful blinkenwall by writing animations and games.</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="1024">Franz Pletz</person>
          <person id="2856">lilafisch</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
          <link href="http://acab.muc.ccc.de/">AllColoursAreBeautiful Project</link>
          <link href="http://gitorious.org/acab">Source Code</link>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4181">
        <start>14:30</start>
        <duration>00:30</duration>
        <room>Saal 2</room>
        <slug>sip_home_gateways_under_fire</slug>
        <title>SIP home gateways under fire</title>
        <subtitle>Source routing attacks applied to SIP</subtitle>
        <track>Hacking</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>The SIP home gateway -- which combines a NAT router, a SIP proxy, and analogue phone adapters -- is the weakest link in a Voice over IP network. SIP's numerous source routing mechanisms share the well-known security weaknesses of IP source routing. The talk discusses possible exploits and countermeasures.</abstract>
        <description>Telephony is steadily moving to Voice over IP, opening up a world of
hacking opportunities. While many security issues have long been addressed
in standardization, real-world VoIP suffers from incomplete and sometimes
broken implementations. SIP home gateways -- which combine a NAT router,
a SIP proxy, and a phone adapter are especially at risk.

The predominant VoIP protocol SIP (Session Initiation Protocol) has
been designed as an -- almost -- stateless protocol. The network elements
responsible for call routing only keep very little and short-lived
state. This makes SIP highly scalable and substantially simplifies
fail-over.

To achieve this, SIP uses source routing mechanisms extensively.
Due to its security weaknesses, the network layer protocols have long
abandoned the idea of source routing, despite its theoretical appeal.
Some IP source routing attacks and countermeasures can be applied to SIP.

The talk will discuss
- how to impersonate somebody else, with seemingly network-asserted identity
- how to trick a home gateway into sending UDP packets to an arbitrary host and port in a victim's LAN.
- how to make a victim's home gateway call an arbitrary number (with some effort)
- how to get material for your off-line password guessing attack
- what SIP providers do about those issues
- how SIP passed the IETF's security reviews
- how home gateway vendors should improve their products to avoid all this mess.
</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="3111">Wolfgang Beck</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4006">
        <start>16:00</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 2</room>
        <slug>diy_synthesizers_and_sound_generators</slug>
        <title>DIY synthesizers and sound generators</title>
        <subtitle>Where does the sound come from?</subtitle>
        <track>Making</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language></language>
        <abstract>At least if you have used all the features of a synthesizer, you probably ask the questions: "How can I modify it? How can I build a synthesizer myself? What features do I personally need?"

This talk covers this topic from a theoretical and technical point of view.</abstract>
        <description>Since commercial synthesizers have been built, the interest in modifying existing synthesizers and building own synthesizers has increased. Nowadays there is a much bigger DIY (Do-It-Yourself) community, and the idea of building own synthesizers and modules has been even merged with the idea of open-source and creative-commons hardware. This gives a wide range of new possibilities.

Another part of the talk will be a quick introduction of less or more known DIY-synthesizer projects and the demonstration of a DIY synthesizer based on MOS 6581-like synthesis (The Commodore SID), which can be built from quite cheap electronic components and give a wide range of possibilities for sound generation and a reasonable sound.

This talk will briefly describe the basics of sound synthesis and what makes it so interesting. A little bit of basic knowledge is recommended, but not necessary.</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="2992">Sylwester</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
          <link href="http://syso.name/w/Main_Page">syso.name wiki pages</link>
          <link href="http://syso.name/w/Propeller_Multimedia_Board">Propeller Multimedia Board</link>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4237">
        <start>18:30</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 2</room>
        <slug>indect_eu_surveillance_project</slug>
        <title>INDECT - an EU-Surveillance Project</title>
        <subtitle></subtitle>
        <track>Society</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>INDECT

The acronym stands for Intelligent Information System Supporting Observation, Searching and Detection for Security of Citizens in Urban Environment. 
A total of 17 partners in nine member states are developing an infrastructure for linking existing surveillance technologies to form one mighty instrument for controlling the people. They are laying the foundation of a European police state, since INDECT's results serve to increase the effectiveness of police operation on the national and European level.
INDECT is funded under the European Commission's Seventh Framework Programme (FP7), the security-related research of which provides &#8364; 1.4 billion Euro for more than 60 partly interlaced projects.
</abstract>
        <description>This Is What the Police Will Work with in the Future:

&#183;Unmanned aerial vehicles/drones with surveillance camera and sensors
&#183;Software (for cameras etc.) to identify supposedly suspicious behavior or hostile intent
&#183;Auto-tracking of mobile objects
&#183;Software (autonomous agents) to monitor virtual spaces such as discussion forums in the Internet or social networks
&#183;Trojan horses which record users&#8217; private computer activity
&#183;Safeguards, such as watermarking, to allow sophisticated controls on recorded images for evidence, and to index, analyse and administer multimedia content (such as video)
&#183;A search engine combining direct search of data from the real and the virtual world
	
The presentation deals with:
- Goals and Partners
- The EU's Current Security Policy
- Ethically Clean - Censorship in Disguise? Ethics Board for INDECT. 
- Critical Assessment of INDECT-Research







</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="2830">Sylvia Johnigk</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
          <link href="http://www.panopticaum-europe.eu">Anti-Indect Seite des FIfF</link>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4085">
        <start>20:30</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 2</room>
        <slug>digitale_spaltung_per_gesetz</slug>
        <title>Digitale Spaltung per Gesetz</title>
        <subtitle>Das Internet und geschaffene soziale Ungleichheit im Alltag von Erwerbslosen</subtitle>
        <track>Society</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>de</language>
        <abstract>Hartz IV-Empfangende brauchen keine internetf&#228;higen Computer, weil sie Fernseher haben. Dieser Ansicht sind deutsche Sozialgerichte und forcieren damit eine digitale Spaltung per Gesetz. Im Zeitalter der digitalen Informations- und Kommunikationsgesellschaft mutet dieser Umstand absurd an, aber eine breite &#246;ffentlichkeitswirksame Debatte steht bisher aus.</abstract>
        <description>Hartz IV-Empfangende brauchen keine internetf&#228;higen Computer, weil sie Fernseher haben. Die Grundversorgung mit Informationen werde laut Landessozialgericht NRW durch Fernsehen und Rundfunk sichergestellt. Dementsprechend gilt auch nur ein Fernseher nicht jedoch ein internetf&#228;higer PC als unpf&#228;ndbar. In den ALG II-Regelleistungen sind Anschaffungskosten f&#252;r einen PC nicht vorgesehen, lediglich 5,80 Euro im Monat f&#252;r Internetdienste und Datenverarbeitung. Dass es in Hamburg mittlerweile eine &#8222;Computer-Tafel&#8220; gibt, zeigt die Unwirklichkeit eines Beschlusses des Landessozialgerichts Bayern, laut dem Hartz IV-Empfangende die Kosten f&#252;r einen PC ansparen k&#246;nnten. In dieser Situation der digitalen Spaltung erforschen wir als Sozialwissenschaftlerinnen an der TU Hamburg-Harburg die Internetnutzung von Erwerbslosen und stellen erste Ergebnisse vor.

Die per Gesetz verordnete digitale Spaltung mutet im Zeitalter der digitalen Informations- und Kommunikationsgesellschaft absurd an. Dass es bisher keine &#246;ffentlichkeitswirksame Debatte gibt, mag auch daran liegen, dass es bisher kaum wissenschaftliche Erkenntnisse dar&#252;ber gibt, welche Bedeutung das Internet im Alltag von Erwerbslosen hat. Diese Frage ist bisher weder in der Erwerbslosen- noch in der Internetforschung untersucht worden. Dabei w&#228;re eine wissenschaftliche Besch&#228;ftigung mit dieser Frage in der Debatte um Ausgrenzung und Teilhabe dringend notwendig. In unserem Forschungsprojekt sind wir dieser Frage anhand von Interviews und Internetsessions mit Erwerbslosen in drei verschiedenen Regionen Deutschlands nachgegangen.

Der Alltag von Menschen im ALG II-Bezug ist in besonderem Ma&#223;e durch prek&#228;re Lebensverh&#228;ltnisse gekennzeichnet. Der Verlust von Erwerbsarbeit bedeutet den Verlust einer zentralen Dimension gesellschaftlicher Teilhabe, der sich auch auf weitere Teilhabeformen wie soziale Nahbeziehungen, Rechte, Kultur und Bildung auswirkt. Welche Rolle spielt nun das Internet in diesem von Ausgrenzungen und sozialen Verwundbarkeiten gepr&#228;gten Alltag? Kann das Internet die eingeschr&#228;nkten Teilhabem&#246;glichkeiten kompensieren? K&#246;nnen Erwerbslose mit Hilfe des Internets Handlungsf&#228;higkeit zur&#252;ckgewinnen? Welche Bedeutung schreiben Erwerbslose dem Zugang zum Internet zu? Wird ein nicht vorhandener oder eingeschr&#228;nkter Internetzugang zu einer weiteren Dimension der Ausgrenzung von Erwerbslosen in der digitalen Wissensgesellschaft und produziert damit soziale Ungleichheit? Wir w&#252;rden gerne mit AktivistInnen diskutieren, wie man gegen die derzeitige gesetzlich gef&#246;rderte doppelte Ausgrenzung von Erwerbslosen vorgehen kann. 
</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="3066">Betje Schwarz</person>
          <person id="3100">Doris Gerbig</person>
          <person id="3063">Kathrin Englert</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
          <link href="http://www.tu-harburg.de/agentec/team/englert.htm">Homepage Kathrin Englert</link>
          <link href="http://www.feministisches-institut.de/erwerbslose/#more-1011">Online-Ver&#246;ffentlichung zum Thema "Digitale Spaltung per Gesetz"</link>
          <link href="http://www.tu-harburg.de/agentec/forschung/bedeutunginternet.htm">Homepage des Forschungsprojekts "Die Bedeutung des Internets f&#252;r gesellschaftliche Teilhabe - am Beispiel allt&#228;glicher Praxen Erwerbsloser"</link>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4055">
        <start>21:45</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 2</room>
        <slug>terrorists_win_exploiting_telecommunications_data</slug>
        <title>Terrorists Win - Exploiting Telecommunications Data Retention?</title>
        <subtitle></subtitle>
        <track>Science</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language></language>
        <abstract>Telecommunications data retention (TDR) has become a reality in most
Western countries. Protagonists claim that the collection of massive
amounts of data on the communication behavior of all individuals
within a country would enable law enforcement agencies to exploit
patterns in the stored data to uncover connections between suspects.
</abstract>
        <description>While this is obviously true for investigations after an incident
happened, there is up to now no critical and sound assessment
publicly available that evaluates whether TDR brings any pro-active
benefits for the above mentioned, justified purposes.
		
In this talk we give for the first time a critical assessment of the
power of TDR based on methods from information theory. To this end we
have employed agent based simulations, which mimic the communication
behavior of a large community including a dark-net of alleged
suspects. The structure and statistics of our telecommunication
simulation, which drive the dynamics of telephone calls and simulated
TDR data, were generated according to known statistics of real-world
telecommunications networks.

Hiding in the unavoidable noise seems to be a passive strategy for
terrorists to circumvent pro-active detection. This stems from a
"needle in the haystack"-problem, that arises due to the small number
of conspirators compared to the number of other participants.

In particular situations and with adopted strategies suspected
terrorists might be able to eventually exploit TDR for their purposes
and take an active approach to hiding in the crowd. Such TDR exploits
would lower the probability of detection by law enforcement agencies
and render TDR a potential security threat. Again, we use our
simulations and our analysis procedure to assess this problem.
</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="2626">Kay Hamacher</person>
          <person id="3165">Stefan Katzenbeisser</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
          <link href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Telecommunications_data_retention">Telecommunications data retention (Wikipedia)</link>
          <link href="http://www.kay-hamacher.de">Author A's homepage</link>
          <link href="http://www.seceng.de">Author B's homepage </link>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4018">
        <start>23:00</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 2</room>
        <slug>frozencache</slug>
        <title>FrozenCache</title>
        <subtitle>Mitigating cold-boot attacks for Full-Disk-Encryption software</subtitle>
        <track>Hacking</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>Cold boot attacks are a major risk for the protection that Full-Disk-Encryption solutions provide. FrozenCache is a general-purpose solution to this attack for x86 based systems that employs a special CPU cache mode known as "Cache-as-RAM". Switching the CPU cache into a special mode forces data to held exclusively in the CPU cache and not to be written to the backing RAM locations, thus safeguarding data from being obtained from RAM by means of cold boot attacks.</abstract>
        <description>A Proof-of-Concept implementation for Linux will be demonstrated and implementation details discussed.</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="2149">Juergen Pabel</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
          <link href="http://blog.akkaya.de/jpabel/">J&#252;rgen's Blog</link>
          <link href="http://frozencache.blogspot.com/">FrozenCache Blog</link>
        </links>
      </event>
    </room>
    <room name="Saal 3">
      <event id="4239">
        <start>12:45</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 3</room>
        <slug>lightning_talks_d3</slug>
        <title>Lightning Talks - Day 3</title>
        <subtitle>where is my community?</subtitle>
        <track>Community</track>
        <type>lightning</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>see 26C3</abstract>
        <description>see 26C3</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="1476">Nick Farr</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4183">
        <start>16:00</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 3</room>
        <slug>safety_on_open_sea</slug>
        <title>Safety on the Open Sea</title>
        <subtitle>Safe navigation with the aid of an open sea chart.</subtitle>
        <track>Science</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>In maritime shipping accurate positioning is vital to preserve damage to life,
ship, and goods. Today, we might tend to think that this problem is
sufficiently solved yet because of the existence of electronic positioning
systems like, most notably, the Global Positioning System (GPS) or the Russian
counterpart GLONASS. This is wrong. Positions in terms of latitude and
longitude just make sense together with an accurate sea chart (and of course,
together with a navigator that is able to translate charting data into
reality).</abstract>
        <description>Sea charts are available of national geospatial agencies and business companies
as hard-copy or as digital maps and dependent on costs one might spend they are
more or less accurate.

In today's open world the idea of making an open sea chart is obvious.
Several projects now started to apply the rules used for the OpenStreetMap,
"...a free editable map of the whole world." (http://www.openstreetmap.org/),
to create a free editable sea chart of the whole world and it turns out to be
much more difficult because of potential serious consequences in case of
charting errors.

A sea chart contains a lot of vital information to a navigator. It has to be
accurate, up to date, and confidential. Since we (the open sea chart community)
cannot just chart every navigational important item on the world we are
dependent on information that was already charted before or on third-party
information. The latter could be for example measurements or GPS tracks of
people that are somehow involved into maritime shipping but not necessarily
into details of marine mapping.  Thus, data accuracy may be questionable but
still valuable.  The fact that unauthenticated people are editing data in an
open database is a big challenge for an open community since safety and
security of life heavily depends on it.

This talk covers the basic principles of sea charts and marine mapping. It
emphasizes the problems of an open sea chart in general and its distinction to
an open street map since requirements to ensure safety at sea are very
different. Data preparation and import of other sources are discussed in
detail, mainly focused on lights and depths. The lecture will connect real
world shortcomings to a pedantic definite IT world for an IT-oriented audience
and approaches IT security from a different angle.</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="2054">Bernhard Fischer</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
          <link href="http://www.openseamap.org/">OpenSeamap Main Page</link>
          <link href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/">OpenStreetmap Main Page</link>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4151">
        <start>17:15</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 3</room>
        <slug>android_geolocation_using_gsm_network</slug>
        <title>Android geolocation using GSM network</title>
        <subtitle>"Where was Waldroid?"</subtitle>
        <track>Hacking</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language></language>
        <abstract>We introduce a new forensic technique that allows to collect users' past locations on most current Android phones, within a few seconds. It becomes possible to tell where the user was at a given time, or where a phone call took place over the last few hours or days.</abstract>
        <description>The attack is based on GSM BTS cell location and little-known Android logging features and can be extended to track a user's activity over long periods of time. 

We will also show how to perform the attack locally and remotely, and ways to protect against these techniques, as well as forensic applications and privacy concerns.

As a part of the presentation we plan to show a live demonstration of both local and remote attacks to retrieve geolocation and activity history of targeted phones. The graphical mapping tool used for the presentation will be released as open source.

* Talk keywords: mobile phone hacking, geolocation, android, privacy, forensics

* Outline:

1. WHY ANDROID?
2. GEOLOCATION: DIFFERENT APPROACHES
3. ATTACK VECTORS
4. SPYING USERS... (GETTING MORE THAN LOCATION: TRACKING CALLS&amp;SMS)
5. PRIVACY CONCERNS
6. FORENSICS
7. HOW TO PROTECT?
8. LIVE DEMO
</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="3098">Renaud Lifchitz</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4187">
        <start>18:30</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 3</room>
        <slug>your_infrastructure_will_kill_you</slug>
        <title>Your Infrastructure Will Kill You</title>
        <subtitle></subtitle>
        <track>Society</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>The past century our infrastructure has seen both massive expansion and heavy centralization.  When it fails, it fails big -- this is the reality of our modern interconnectedness.  We live in a world of crumbling bridges and bankrupt states, and our infrastructure will kill us.  The people we&#8217;re relying on to keep us safe are trying to accomplish long-term risk management with short-term thinking.  So, what now?  We can't opt out, but we can become more resilient, and we can start thinking about risk differently.</abstract>
        <description>In this talk, we'll look at threat modeling in the real world, six ways to die, failing states, that big party in the desert, the failure of the humanitarian project, algae and the U.S. military, large-scale natural disasters, the power grid, and many other things.  The problems we face are big in every sense of the word -- they involve some of the biggest things we've ever built -- but the solutions may not be.  Can non-governmental networks step up when governments fail to provide basic services?  Can we avoid a further expansion of neoliberalism in a post-infrastructural state?  Are the power structures embedded in our infrastructure cultural destiny?  What happens when maker culture grows up?

Come find out, while you still have a choice.
</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="2672">Eleanor Saitta</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4145">
        <start>23:00</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 3</room>
        <slug>automation_human_interfaces_spoilers_reverse_green_decel_whats_it_doing_now</slug>
        <title>"Spoilers, Reverse Green, DECEL!" or "What's it doing now?"</title>
        <subtitle>Thoughts on the Automation and its Human interfaces on Airplanes</subtitle>
        <track>Science</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>Getting the interfaces right to computers controlling complex and dangerous machines such as commercial airliners is crucial. I will present a successful accident analysis method and talk about interface design problems, ideas for solutions, methods for understanding causal control flow. There will be some spectacular aviation accident videos and stories of bad luck, bad design, bad decisions, and a hero that managed to turn a near-catastrophe into an accident without fatalities.
</abstract>
        <description>Getting the Interface right can be crucial.

So does an understanding of the underlying logic, and knowledge of correct procedures when operating complex devices.

Modern airliners are incredibly complex machines, no person can fully understand what is going on. This starts at simple things like fuel systems (e. g. the B777 has only two engines and three fuel tanks, how complicated can that be? Surprisingly so.) and goes on to autopilots, autothrottle systems, FADECs (Full Authority Digital Engine Control), Flight Management, Guidance and Envelope Computers (FMGEC), digital fly-by-wire systems, weight computations etc.

Apart from the largely unsolved problems of how to create software for these systems that is demonstrably extremely reliable (in commercial aviation we're talking about probablities of dangerous failures of 1 in a billion flight hours: testing just won't do), there is the underrated question of getting the interface right.

What to annunciate to the crew and when, and in which form? Some accidents and incidents are directly related to a flight crew being confused by the annunciations, or didn't know how to react properly to seemingly unrelated warnings. At other times, a pertinent and important warning is suppressed because another, ostensibly more important warning inhibited the other one.

I'll be talking about some accidents that we have analysed using Why-Because-Analysis (see http://www.rvs.uni-bielefeld.de/research/WBA/) in which the interface and the automation played a role. I will also be talking about some design principles to guide interface design and interactive safety.
</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="3094">Bernd Sieker</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
          <link href="http://www.rvs.uni-bielefeld.de/research/WBA/">The Why-Because Analysis Page</link>
        </links>
      </event>
    </room>
  </day>
  <day date="2010-12-30" index="4">
    <room name="Saal 1">
      <event id="4221">
        <start>11:30</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 1</room>
        <slug>omg_wtf_pdf</slug>
        <title>OMG WTF PDF</title>
        <subtitle>What you didn't know about Acrobat</subtitle>
        <track>Hacking</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>Ambiguities in the PDF specification means that no two PDF parsers will see a file in the same way. This leads to many opportunities for exploit obfuscation.</abstract>
        <description>PDFs are currently the greatest vector for drive-by (malware installing) attacks and targeted attacks on business and government. A/V technology is extraordinarily poor at detecting these. [Well, except for my company of course, we detect them all. :] The PDF format itself is so diverse and vague, that an A/V needs to be 100% bug-compatible with the parser in the vulnerable PDF reader. [Not that there are any A/Vs which actually parse PDFs yet.]</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="3131">Julia Wolf</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4089">
        <start>12:45</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 1</room>
        <slug>ich_sehe_nicht_dass_wir_nicht_zustimmen_werden</slug>
        <title>Ich sehe nicht, dass wir nicht zustimmen werden</title>
        <subtitle>Die Sprache des politischen Verrats und seiner Rechtfertigung</subtitle>
        <track>Society</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language></language>
        <abstract>Der Vortrag zeigt auf, wie sich Politiker rechtfertigen, wenn sie gegen ihre Argumentation und die &#220;berzeugungen entscheiden oder handeln, f&#252;r die sie stehen. Es ergibt sich dabei eine extreme Zwangslage, denn es ist oft nicht so einfach m&#246;glich, die zuvor vorgebrachten Argumente aufzugeben. Also muss auf Leerformeln, Nebelkerzen, Scheinargumente und spezielle grammatische Mittel zur&#252;ckgegriffen werden, die die Regresspflicht mindern (Konjunktive, doppelte Verneinungen, Modalpartikeln usw.); dabei sind Kunstgriffe n&#246;tig, die &#252;ber die inzwischen hinl&#228;nglich bekannte Leyen-Rhetorik hinausgehen.</abstract>
        <description>2010 war ein Jahr der politischen Ver&#228;nderung. Dabei ver&#228;nderten sich auch politische Einstellungen: so wollen die Gr&#252;nen im D&#252;sseldorfer Landtag pl&#246;tzlich f&#252;r den Jugendmedienschutzstaatsvertrag stimmen, den sie in der Opposition verhindern wollten. Reinhard B&#252;tikofer stimmt dem Gallo-Bericht zu Urheber- und Leistungsschutz zu. Und schon 2009 glaubten gr&#252;ne Abgeordnete, nicht gegen das Zugangserschwerungsgesetz stimmen zu m&#252;ssen. Alle rechtfertigten sich &#8211; oder versuchten es zumindest. Auch in den anderen Parteien gab es Ver&#228;nderungen: Der Innenminister gab sich mal mehr mal weniger aufgeschlossen, wenn es um Netzpolitik ging. Die CDU forderte eine verl&#228;ssliche Politik beim Bahnhofsbau, vollzog aber den Ausstieg aus dem Atomausstieg. Die SPD wollte mal wieder Netzpartei sein und forderte mehr Zeitungslekt&#252;re f&#252;r Sch&#252;ler. Wenn man wenige oder keine Argumente hat, weicht man auf Scheinargumente aus; was bleibt aber, wenn man in die eine Richtung argumentiert und in die andere Richtung entscheidet? Die Sprache des politischen Verrats und seiner Rechtfertigung gibt Aufschluss. 

Zu Wort kommen unter anderen: Matthias Bolte und Reinhard B&#252;tikofer, Thomas de Maizi&#232;re, Jan Eumann und Politiker aus Stuttgart. </description>
        <persons>
          <person id="47">maha/Martin Haase</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4124">
        <start>14:00</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 1</room>
        <slug>three_jobs_that_journalists_will_do_in_2050</slug>
        <title>Three jobs that journalists will do in 2050</title>
        <subtitle>Why future media may be more powerful (and more subversive) than ever before</subtitle>
        <track>Society</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>Print media are dying, but what is rising up to take their place? In this presentation, I'll answer that question by describing three new kinds of jobs for journalists that do not exist in mainstream print media. These jobs are: hacker journalist, data-mining reporter, and crowd engineer. I'll be describing what these jobs entail, and current examples of organizations already employing people to do them.</abstract>
        <description>My observations in this presentation are based on the nearly twenty years I have written for traditional print as well as new media publications, including zines like Bad Subjects and 2600, as well as mainstream media outlets like Wired and the Washington Post. I also created io9.com, the world's most widely-read blog devoted to science and science fiction. As I've watched friends and colleagues suffer through layoffs in the publishing industry, I've also seen the rise of new kinds of journalists who use technology to break stories in ways that would have been impossible even five years ago.

Hacker journalists use everything from Perl scripts to open source mapping platforms to do investigative reporting (examples include writing at Ars Technica, as well as people working with the Ushahidi mapping platform). Data-mining reporters are people who analyze vast amounts of data to investigate issues from war crimes (using services like Wikileaks) to the stock market "flash crash". Crowd engineers work on crowd-sourced news sites like Reddit and Metafilter, writing algorithms and community software that makes it easy for people to share information. Like editors, crowd engineers can be very powerful figures who determine which information rises to the top.

What these new journalists have in common is a newfound ability to aggregate and analyze information on a massive scale. Ultimately I'll explore how this changes the playing field in media, and why journalists of the future may be more powerful than ever before.</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="3083">Annalee Newitz</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4301">
        <start>16:00</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 1</room>
        <slug>flow_analysis_of_internet_activities</slug>
        <title>How the Internet sees you</title>
        <subtitle>demonstrating what activities most ISPs see you doing on the Internet</subtitle>
        <track>Society</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language></language>
        <abstract>On the Internet one tends to think that one is pretty much safe from poking eyes. Taps in most countries can only be established after a judge has issued a warrant, thus upto such a tap is succesfully deployed  one might think one is pretty much in the clear.</abstract>
        <description>Most ISPs though actually employ a toolset comprising one of various NetFlow, IPFIX or sFlow protocols to do trend monitoring, billing and of course, the ability to try and establish which connections a certain IP address is making.

During the CCC conference we will monitor the CCC network with NetFlow, collecting and directly anonimizing this information on IP basis. We will map a couple of well-known websites/trackers to a private IP range and preserving these mappings, while anonimizing the rest of the IP addresses, thus your anonimity is safe and please be yourself while using the network. Flow data will not be stored, thus we won't be able to go back and re-analyze the information.

As a collector/analyzer we will be using the Anaphera tool by IBM Zurich Research Laboratory [1]. This tool is used in IBM datacenters and by customers of IBM worldwide for detecting malicious/unknown network traffic, traffic trending, anomaly detection, growth prognosis and billing.

We'll be explaining the intriciate parts about NetFlow, IPFIX and sFlow, what the technologies are and how they work, hopping briefly in the big difference with taps and what they could see when they are deployed and also what we don't see now and what gets lost in the noise.

We will be showing you what information and details can be taken from a flow based tool, so that you know what can be seen by ISPs around the world.</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="1395">Jeroen Massar</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
          <link href="http://www.zurich.ibm.com/aurora/">AURORA: Traffic analysis and visualization</link>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4230">
        <start>17:15</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 1</room>
        <slug>security_nightmares</slug>
        <title>Security Nightmares</title>
        <subtitle></subtitle>
        <track>Community</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>de</language>
        <abstract>Was hat sich im letzten Jahr im Bereich IT-Sicherheit getan? Welche neuen Entwicklungen haben sich ergeben? Welche neuen Buzzwords und Trends waren zu sehen?</abstract>
        <description>Wie immer wagen wir den Ausblick auf das Jahr 2011 und dar&#252;ber hinaus, denn was wir wirklich wissen wollen, ist ja schlie&#223;lich: Was kommt in Zukunft auf uns zu? Wir werden au&#223;erdem fr&#252;here Voraussagen hinsichtlich des Eintreffens unserer Weissagungen pr&#252;fen.</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="9">Frank Rieger</person>
          <person id="129">Ron</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4299">
        <start>18:30</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 1</room>
        <slug>closing_event</slug>
        <title>Abschlussveranstaltung</title>
        <subtitle></subtitle>
        <track>Community</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract></abstract>
        <description></description>
        <persons>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
    </room>
    <room name="Saal 2">
      <event id="4098">
        <start>11:30</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 2</room>
        <slug>tor_is_peace_software_freedom_is_slavery</slug>
        <title>Tor is Peace, Software Freedom is Slavery, Wikipedia is Truth</title>
        <subtitle>The political philosophy of the Internet</subtitle>
        <track>Society</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language></language>
        <abstract>The Internet began as state-sponsored anarchy, but it is now the tool of first resort for dissidents and propagandists alike. The poster-child project of the Free Software Movement runs on the authority of a single person; the rest clash over the very definition of the word 'free'. A company which pictured itself as smashing Big Brother is now seen as one of the perceived secretive and authoritarian in the industry; and for another, 'Don't Be Evil' is proving to be a challenging motto to live by.</abstract>
        <description>This talk aims to present a view of the societies of Internet from the perspective of political philosophy. *Political philosophy is not politics*, in the same way that computer science is not programming. It's not the politics about the Internet, but the politics *of* the Internet. Even so, events at any particular place or time just provide examples to be studied. Political philosophy is meta-politics, it's about the trends in politics and the theories we use to understand them.

Real-world political systems have striking parallels in the evolution of the Internet: there was primitive anarchy before Eternal September, the era of walled gardens resembled that of Ancient Greek city-states, which were succeeded by more-or-less liberal regimes following the geographical territories of real-world governments. Because of its rapid evolution, mass participation, and highly complex human interaction, the Internet should be subjected to the sorts of questions that political philosophers ask. On the Internet, what is freedom? Do we have obligations to those in control? To each other? What rights do we have? What can we own?

Once we know the way it is, we can ask how it should be...</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="3067">Adam</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4003">
        <start>13:00</start>
        <duration>00:30</duration>
        <room>Saal 2</room>
        <slug>cybernetics_for_the_masses</slug>
        <title>Cybernetics for the Masses</title>
        <subtitle>implants, sensory extension and silicon - all for you!</subtitle>
        <track>Hacking</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>Lightning talk on biohacking, complete with cyborg speaker, implant demonstrations, and knowledge of how to hack your own perception of electromagnetic radiation for approximately thirty Euros.</abstract>
        <description>A talk on what's become my specialty - biohacking, or meathacking, whatever you wanna call it. I've got a full set of home-brewed implants, a subdermal RFID, a sort of cult on the Internet plus things like proven designs for cheap EM sensory nodes, experimental verification of that shit I'm claiming, etc. I have videos of procedures, photos of what I've been doing and the like, and will happily make gory slides for all to see. Can do demos of the EM nodes and RFID chip as well. 

I want to talk about the grinder movement - underground biohacking - it's my life. Thus, my article in H+ Magazine: "A call to arms for biohackers".
</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="2989">Lepht Anonym</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
          <link href="http://sapiensanonym.blogspot.com">Blog with documentation of all this.</link>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="3983">
        <start>13:45</start>
        <duration>00:30</duration>
        <room>Saal 2</room>
        <slug>hackers_and_computer_science</slug>
        <title>Hackers and Computer Science</title>
        <subtitle></subtitle>
        <track>Hacking</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>Although most academics and industry practitioners regard "hacking" as mostly ad-hoc, a loose collection of useful tricks essentially random in nature, I will argue that hacking has in fact become a "distinct research and engineering discipline" with deep underlying engineering ideas and insights. Although not yet formally defined as such, it are these ideas and insights that drive the great contributions that hacking has been making to our understanding of computing, including the challenges of handling complexity, composition, and security in complex systems. I will argue that hacking uncovers and helps to understand (and teach) fundamental issues that go to the heart of Computer Science as we know it, and will try to formulate several such fundamental principles which I have learned from hacker research.</abstract>
        <description>At some point I realized that I was learning more about what really matters in computer science from hacker conventions, Phrack, Uninformed, and other hacker sources than from any academic source. Moreover, it wasn't just about exploits and vulnerabilities, it was about how systems were really designed, as opposed to how developers thought and students were taught they were. Then I realized that the reason for vulnerabilities that kept on giving were quite
deeply theoretical and involved, e.g., theory of computation and information theory. Very little of this was quoted or understood in the academic publications.

In this talk I will give a retrospective of hacker research that I believe has priority in developing or rediscovering important scientific ideas that define the discipline of information security. I will also argue that "hacking" has de-facto become a distinct engineering discipline with its own special methods and principles.

1. Hackers invented "cross-layer analysis" methodology.

Hackers deal with trust properties of software, hardware, and human-computer systems. Other disciplines claim to study these properties, but hacker approach is radically different: while others focus of *layered designs* (like the OSI networking model or the application-library-system calls-kernel internals-drivers), hacking is essentially *cross-layer*.

In a word, hackers essentially invented security analysis that focuses on trust assumptions in interactions between layers in multi-layer composed systems. It is not formalized to academic standards, but it's there and it delivers.

In retrospect, the emergence of an engineering discipline that analyzed the trust effects of the prevaling practical method of developing complex computer systems - composing them out of mostly independently developed and tested components - was to be expected. Such analysis was sorely needed and would arise even if these issues were continually ignored by the recognized experts and authorities. As it stands, hacker research arose to fill this gap.

Whereas for a regular developer the layers below or above are implicitly trusted to behave as specified (or at least as described in tutorials), hackers focus on how the layers actually interact, and how data and control actually flow through the layers.

That is why in-depth rootkits (like Phrack 59:5, palmers@team-teso and similar) are the best possible reading for understand OS structure. I assign it in all my OS-related courses. That is why session hijacking through packet injection and other "Black Ops" a-la Ptacek, Newsham, and Kaminsky is best for understanding how TCP/IP stacks work: it shows exactly what data structures are kept by kernels to present the illusion of a session over stateless IP, and how they are controlled.

2. "Security is not Composable"

Many of the best hacks are based on an interplay between composition of relatively secure parts resulting in new properties that make the composed system insecure. To a large extent, Hacking as a research discipline is a study of this phenomenon (which I will illustrate with examples from networks and systems).

From the theory standpoint, for a system that is a composition of several sufficiently complex parts, there is no general algorithm or formal method to deduce properties of the composed system even if properties of parts are known. (This can be reduced to the Halting Problem or, equivalently, to Rice's Theorem).

I will give examples of insecure system design based on simple assumptions about the compositional properties that cannot actually be verified in any algorithmic way -- and, as a result, these systems remain badly broken despite efforts to fix them. These systems will remain untrustworthy and yielding 0-days because their security is based on an undecidable problem that no amount of programming can solve.

A prime example - taken to the next level of rigor in a major break-through by Len Sassaman and Meredith Patterson announced this year - is the case of X.509 certificates. It depends on the computations involved in parsing of the certificate signing request and the signed certificate by the CA and the browser respectively being equivalent (i. e., yielding the same result). However, the design of the X.509 protocol makes it computationally impossible to check this equivalence - and so the certificate system will keep on giving. Mostly likely, there is no "good enough" solution, unless a well-defined
intermediary class of data structures involved is defined.

Another example of the same thing is NIDS traffic re-assembly. The efficacy of NIDS depends on the re-assembly computation giving the same result on the NIDS and the target - and this is, in general, also computationally impossible (undecidable), with no "good enough" solution either.

3. Hackers re-define what "computation" means.

Theory of computation concerns itself with proving what computing environments can and cannot do - e. g., that regular expressions cannot parse recursive structures (not that it is not being attempted, the last high-profile example being IE's regexp-based anti-XSS rewriting feature which gave rise to a whole new kind of exploits precisely because of this inability).

Designers and developers base security of their systems on similar trust assumptions of what the systems can and cannot do. The problem is, they do not understand what computations their systems are *actually* capable of.

From the early days of Aleph1 stack-smashing, hacking has a great history of exposing extra computational power in systems, and in demonstrating "weird" computations that were thought to be impossible. Hackers have been exposing unexpected "weird machines" actually contained in traditional computing environments, which supported unexpected programming models, with exploits as their "programs".

Exploit development as a discipline is about recognizing a "weird machine" inherent in the target (which is usually Turing-complete or close) and writing code for it (in its "weird" instruction set, which may include calls to library functions, system calls, or just reachable pieces code from app to firmware).

It's all about programming "platforms within platforms within platforms".

A prime example is the story of developing the "return-to-known code" idea, from the original "return-to-libc" exploits first published by Solar Designer in 1997, through the detailed technique explanation in Phrack 2000-2001 (58:4, 59:5), to the recent fully featured compiler for kernel rootkits by Hund, Holz, and Freiling. The idea of such compilers, however, has been circulated in the hacker community since at least 2001, as I will show.

It took about ten years for academia to recognize the power of this idea, which got named "Return-oriented Programming" or "ROP" in 2008.

The idea that an exploit - that is, an actual program in its own right, executing on a "weird machine" - could contain *no* native executable code, and thus instead of looking for "malicious code" one had to watch out for "malicious computation" (this term itself coined in 2008) - would have been impossible without hacker research.

In short, hacker research had re-defined the very idea of computation.

4. DoD "Orange Book" ideas re-born in hacker OS hardening patches.

I will show how the classic 1970s ideas about building secure systems, such as those of the DoD "Rainbow series" and Tagged architectures, while long ignored by the commodity computing vendors like Intel, have been re-born in hacker hardening patches such as OpenWall, PaX, grsecurity patches, etc., and other creative uses of the x86 segmentation system, extra page table entry bits, and split TLB.

I will give a historical perspective of these advances, from OpenWall to ShadowWalker and beyond.

I will argue that it was hacker research and hacker proof-of-concepts that finally caused the industry to recognize the value of and implement hardware NX protection and introduce NX-based features like DEP into mainstream OS (I am indebted to FX for major parts of this argument).

5. The hacker development of the debugger into a Turing-complete environment.

It is a fact that hackers (and, in particular, vuln dev and RE communities) have been the leading producer of debuggers ever increasing in power, and have in fact changed the very idea of the conventional debugger, by making it into a Turing-complete environment.

This research involved a deeper understanding of how to use hardware trapping - including how to trap complex events such as "a page that has been recently written to by a user process was used to fetch an instruction from" (OllyBone).

It opened new directions for security policy mechanisms, reference monitor design, etc., in both academia and industry (of which I will give examples).

6. Trust relationships as first-class networking objects.

I will describe how hacker research into network deceptions and trust relationship mapping in networks created the methodology and the industry of network security assessment.

</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="3201">Sergey</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4168">
        <start>14:30</start>
        <duration>00:30</duration>
        <room>Saal 2</room>
        <slug>a_framework_for_automated_architecture_independent_gadget_search</slug>
        <title>A framework for automated architecture-independent gadget search</title>
        <subtitle>CCC edition</subtitle>
        <track>Hacking</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language></language>
        <abstract>We demonstrate that automated, architecture-independent gadget search is possible. Gadgets are code fragments which can be used to build unintended programs from existing code in memory. Our contribution is a framework of algorithms capable of locating a Turing-complete gadget set.</abstract>
        <description>Translating machine code into an intermediate language allows our framework to be used for many different CPU architectures with minimal architecture-dependent adjustments. We define the paradigm of free-branch instructions to succinctly capture which gadgets will be found by our framework and investigate side effects of the gadgets produced. Furthermore we discuss architectural idiosyncrasies for several widely spread CPU architectures and how they need to be taken into account by the generic algorithms when locating gadgets.</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="3108">kornau</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4236">
        <start>16:00</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 2</room>
        <slug>international_cyber_jurisdiction</slug>
        <title>International Cyber Jurisdiction</title>
        <subtitle>Kill Switching&#8221; Cyberspace, Cyber Criminal Prosecution &amp; Jurisdiction Hopping</subtitle>
        <track>Society</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>Concepts of sovereignty, freedom, privacy and intellectual property become amorphous when discussing territories that only exists as far as the Internet connects. International cyber jurisdiction is supported by a complicated web of international law and treaties. Jurisdiction hopping, a technique that is becoming popular for controversial content, is one we have used for the U.S. 1st Amendment censorship-resistant and non-profit hosting company,  Project DOD, by using PRQ's services in Sweden. This technique is used to place assets in a diverse, but accessible, web of countries in which that content may be legal in the hosting country, but may have legal complications in the country in which it is accessed. As ownership and protection of property becomes a concept that is difficult to maintain across boundaries that are not easily distinguishable, can the U.S. "kill-switch" parts of the Internet and under what authority can it be done? Similarly, the geographic challenges to international cyber criminal law &#8211; and the feasibility of new sovereign nations &#8211; will be analyzed. </abstract>
        <description>When a cybercrime is committed in a country in which the electronic communication did not originate, there is difficulty prosecuting the crime without being able to physically apprehend a subject that is virtually within &#8211; and physically without &#8211; a country's boarders. Similarly, a technique called jurisdiction hopping can be used to place assets in a diverse, but accessible, web of countries in which that content may be legal in the hosting country, but is not in the country in which it is accessed. Lastly, if the U.S. attempts to isolate damage by cutting off Internet connections, under what authority can it be done?

This presentation will discuss the types of international laws and treaties that may be cited in the event of extradition of cyber criminals, legal and geographic challenges &#8211; such as new sovereign nations &#8211;  to jurisdiction hopping and the authority with which the U.S. may "kill switch" the Internet. I will also discuss the practical example of where, as a result of our Project DOD case in U.S. Federal court, we have put non-copyright infringing materials on PRQ's servers in Sweden to reduce the incidences of Digital Millennium Copyright Act&#8217;s "Take Down" infringement notices that are illegitimate. </description>
        <persons>
          <person id="3136">TiffanyRad</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4261">
        <start>17:15</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 2</room>
        <slug>key_recovery_attacks_rc4</slug>
        <title>News Key Recovery Attacks on RC4/WEP</title>
        <subtitle></subtitle>
        <track>Hacking</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language></language>
        <abstract>In this paper, we present several weaknesses in the stream cipher RC4.
First, we present a technique to automatically reveal linear
correlations in the PRGA of RC4. </abstract>
        <description>With this method, 48 new exploitable
correlations have been discovered. Then we bind these new biases in
the PRGA with known KSA weaknesses to provide practical key recovery
attacks. Henceforth, we apply a similar technique on RC4 as a black
box, i.e. the secret key words as input and the keystream words as
output.	Our objective is to exhaustively find linear correlations
between these elements. Thanks to this technique, 9 new exploitable
correlations have been revealed. Finally, we exploit these weaknesses
on RC4 to some practical examples, such as the WEP protocol. We show
that these correlations lead to a key recovery attack on WEP with only
9,800 encrypted packets (less than 20 seconds), instead of
24,200 for the best previous attack.
</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="3154">Martin Vuagnoux</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
    </room>
    <room name="Saal 3">
      <event id="4300">
        <start>12:45</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Saal 3</room>
        <slug>lightning_talks_d4</slug>
        <title>Lightning Talks - Day 4</title>
        <subtitle>where is my community?</subtitle>
        <track>Community</track>
        <type>lightning</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>see 26C3</abstract>
        <description>see 26C3</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="1476">Nick Farr</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
      <event id="4193">
        <start>17:15</start>
        <duration>00:45</duration>
        <room>Saal 3</room>
        <slug>having_fun_with_rtp</slug>
        <title>Having fun with RTP</title>
        <subtitle>&#8222;Who is speaking???&#8220; </subtitle>
        <track>Hacking</track>
        <type>lecture</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>A lot of people are interested and involved in voice over IP security. Most of the effort is concentrated on the security of the signalling protocols. This talk is focussing on the security of the voice part involved in todays voice over IP world. It is the result of the questions that I had to ask myself while i was debugging audio quality problems of customers and implementing a RTP stack from scratch.</abstract>
        <description>The talk gives an introduction on the shortcomings of the Realtime Transport Protocol (RTP), how systems attempt to work around them and how they introduce security vulnerabilites. A few short demonstrations will give an idea on how they can be exploited in the real world (denial of service, man in the middle attacks, call redirection).
The last part of the talk will discuss some solutions to fix those vulnerabilities.</description>
        <persons>
          <person id="2958">kapejod</person>
        </persons>
        <links>
        </links>
      </event>
    </room>
  </day>
</schedule>